<?xml version="1.0" ?
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2019//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_190101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Owner="NLM" Status="MEDLINE"><PMID Version="1">33864783</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-0007</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>207</Volume><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Experimental eye research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Exp Eye Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Temporal evolution of the biological response to laser-induced refractive index change (LIRIC) in rabbit corneas.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>108579</StartPage><MedlinePgn>108579</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.exer.2021.108579</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0014-4835(21)00144-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Laser-induced refractive index change (LIRIC) is a new, non-incisional, non-ablative, femtosecond photo-modification technique being developed for vision correction in humans. Prior, exvivo studies showed intra-tissue refractive index change to induce minimal cell death, restricted to the laser focal zone in the corneal stroma, and with no observable damage to the epithelium or endothelium. Here, we used live rabbits to ascertain longer-term consequences of LIRIC in vivo. Specifically, we assessed cell death, fibrosis, corneal nerve distribution, endothelial cell density, and corneal structure for up to 3 months after LIRIC. A +2.5 D gradient-index LIRIC Fresnel lens was inscribed inside 20 applanated corneas of Dutch Belted rabbits, over a circular region of the mid-stroma measuring 4.5&#160;mm in diameter. Twelve additional rabbit eyes were used as applanation-only controls to differentiate the effects of laser treatment and suction applanation on biological and structural parameters. In vivo optical measurements were performed pre-operatively, then immediately, 2, 4, and 12 weeks after the procedure, to measure endothelial cell density and changes in corneal structure. Groups of four rabbits were sacrificed at 4&#160;hours, 2, 4, and 12 weeks after LIRIC for histological determinations; the TUNEL assay was used to evaluate cell death, H&amp;E staining was used to assess inflammatory infiltration, and immunostaining for &#945;-smooth muscle actin (&#945;-SMA) and &#946;III tubulin (Tuj-1) was performed to assess myofibroblast differentiation and corneal nerve distribution, respectively. Consistent with prior ex vivo data, only minimal cell death was observed in the laser focal zone, with TUNEL-positive cells restricted to the stromal region of refractive index change 4&#160;h after LIRIC. No TUNEL-positive cells were evident anywhere in the cornea 2, 4, or 12 weeks after LIRIC. Applanation-only corneas were completely TUNEL-negative. Neither LIRIC-treated nor applanation-only eyes exhibited &#945;-SMA-positive staining or altered corneal nerve distributions at any of the time points examined. In vivo confocal imaging revealed normal endothelial cell densities in all eyes (whether LIRIC-treated or applanation-only) at all time points. Optical coherence tomography showed suction applanation to cause a temporary decrease in central corneal thickness, which returned to normal within 4&#160;h. Corneas into which LIRIC Fresnel lenses were written while applanated did not undergo major structural or shape changes beyond the temporary thinning already described for suction applanation. The present findings suggest that LIRIC patterns, which generated a clinically-relevant refractive correction in the mid-stromal region of live rabbit corneas, induced little-to-no disruption to corneal structure and biology for 3 months after the procedure. This affirms the relative safety of LIRIC and predicts that compared to traditional laser vision correction surgeries, common post-operative complications such as dry eye, haze, or patient discomfort may be entirely avoided.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#169; 2021 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wozniak</LastName><ForeName>Kaitlin T</ForeName><Initials>KT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Institute of Optics, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Center for Visual Science, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Flaum Eye Institute, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14642, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Butler</LastName><ForeName>Sam C</ForeName><Initials>SC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clerio Vision Inc., Rochester, NY, 14618, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Xu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Flaum Eye Institute, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14642, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ellis</LastName><ForeName>Jonathan D</ForeName><Initials>JD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clerio Vision Inc., Rochester, NY, 14618, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Knox</LastName><ForeName>Wayne H</ForeName><Initials>WH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Institute of Optics, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Center for Visual Science, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huxlin</LastName><ForeName>Krystel R</ForeName><Initials>KR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Institute of Optics, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Center for Visual Science, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Flaum Eye Institute, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14642, USA. Electronic address: khuxlin@ur.rochester.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P30 EY001319</GrantID><Acronym>EY</Acronym><Agency>NEI NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 EY015836</GrantID><Acronym>EY</Acronym><Agency>NEI NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013486">Research Support, U.S. Gov't, Non-P.H.S.</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Exp Eye Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370707</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0014-4835</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D000818">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D002452">Cell Count</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D016923">Cell Death</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D003315">Cornea</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000294">innervation</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D003319">Corneal Stroma</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000503">physiopathology</QualifierName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000601">surgery</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D048988">Corneal Surgery, Laser</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000379">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D004728">Endothelium, Corneal</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000473">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D005260">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D005355">Fibrosis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D018613">Microscopy, Confocal</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D009882">Ophthalmic Nerve</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000502">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D011817">Rabbits</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D012029">Refraction, Ocular</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000502">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D041623">Tomography, Optical Coherence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D014792">Visual Acuity</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000502">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D014945">Wound Healing</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000502">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Corneal endothelial cells</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Corneal nerves</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Myofibroblasts</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Refractive surgery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Stroma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TUNEL</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wound healing</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2020</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2021</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33864783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1697484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8187327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.exer.2021.108579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0014-4835(21)00144-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ambr&#243;sio R Jr, Tervo T, Wilson SE, 2008. LASIK-associated dry eye and neurotrophic epitheliopathy: pathophysiology and strategies for prevention and treatment. Journal of refractive surgery 24, 396&#8211;407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18500091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aron-Rosa DS, Boulnoy JL, Carr&#233; F, Delacour J, Gross M, Lacour M, Olivo JC, Timsit JC, 1986. Excimer laser surgery of the cornea: qualitative and quantitative aspects of photoablation according to the energy density. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 12, 27&#8211;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3958947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baum J, Maurice D, McCarey B, 1984. The active and passive transport of water across the corneal endothelium. Experimental eye research 39, 335&#8211;342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6499954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belmonte C, Acosta MC, Gallar J, 2004. Neural basis of sensation in intact and injured corneas. Experimental eye research 78, 513&#8211;525.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15106930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks DR, Brown NS, Savage DE, Wang C, Knox WH, Ellis JD, 2014. Precision large field scanning system for high numerical aperture lenses and application to femtosecond micromachining of ophthalmic materials. Review of Scientific Instruments 85, 065107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24985852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>B&#252;hren J, Nagy L, Swanton JN, Kenner S, MacRae S, Phipps RP, Huxlin KR, 2009. Optical effects of anti-TGF&#946; treatment after photorefractive keratectomy in a cat model. Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 50, 634&#8211;643.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2753416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18952913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campos M, Szerenyi K, Lee M, McDonnell JM, Lopez PF, McDonnell PJ, 1994. Keratocyte loss after corneal deepithelialization in primates and rabbits. Archives of ophthalmology 112, 254&#8211;260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8311779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan A, Manche EE, 2011. Effect of preoperative pupil size on quality of vision after wavefront-guided LASIK. Ophthalmology 118, 736&#8211;741.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21093922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding L, Blackwell R, K&#252;nzler JF, Knox WH, 2006. Large refractive index change in silicone-based and non-silicone-based hydrogel polymers induced by femtosecond laser micro-machining. Optics express 14, 11901&#8211;11909.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19529613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doughty MJ, Cullen AP, 1990. Long&#8208;term effects of a single dose of ultraviolet&#8208;B on albino rabbit cornea&#8211;II. Deturgescence and fluid pump assessed in vitro. Photochemistry and photobiology 51, 439&#8211;449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2343062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erie JC, McLaren JW, Hodge DO, Bourne WM, 2005. Recovery of corneal subbasal nerve density after PRK and LASIK. American journal of ophthalmology 140, 1059&#8211;1064. e1051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16376651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espana E, Ti S, Grueterich M, Touhami A, Tseng S, 2003. Corneal stromal changes following reconstruction by ex vivo expanded limbal epithelial cells in rabbits with total limbal stem cell deficiency. British journal of ophthalmology 87, 1509&#8211;1514.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1920578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14660463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan-Paul NI, Li J, Miller JS, Florakis GJ, 2002. Night vision disturbances after corneal refractive surgery. Survey of ophthalmology 47, 533&#8211;546.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12504738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandara-Montano GA, Ivansky A, Savage DE, Ellis JD, Knox WH, 2015. Femtosecond laser writing of freeform gradient index microlenses in hydrogel-based contact lenses. Optical Materials Express 5, 2257&#8211;2271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandara-Montano GA, Stoy V, Dudi&#269; M, Petr&#225;k V, Ha&#353;kovcov&#225; K, Knox WH, 2017. Large optical phase shifts in hydrogels written with femtosecond laser pulses: elucidating the role of localized water concentration changes. Optical Materials Express 7, 3162&#8211;3180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao J, Gelber-Schwalb TA, Addeo JV, Stern ME, 1997. Apoptosis in the rabbit cornea after photorefractive keratectomy. Cornea 16, 200&#8211;208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9071534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He J, Bazan NG, Bazan HE, 2010. Mapping the entire human corneal nerve architecture. Experimental eye research 91, 513&#8211;523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2939211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20650270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helena MC, Baerveldt F, Kim W-J, Wilson SE, 1998. Keratocyte apoptosis after corneal surgery. Investigative Ophthalmology and Visual Science 39, 276&#8211;283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9477983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hindman HB, DeMagistris M, Callan C, McDaniel T, Bubel T, Huxlin KR, 2019. Impact of topical anti-fibrotics on corneal nerve regeneration in vivo. Experimental eye research 181, 49&#8211;60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6443430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30660507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huxlin KR, Hindman HB, Jeon K-I, B&#252;hren J, MacRae S, DeMagistris M, Ciufo D, Sime PJ, Phipps RP, 2013. Topical rosiglitazone is an effective anti-scarring agent in the cornea. PloS one 8, e70785.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3733781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23940641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeon K-I, Hindman HB, Bubel T, McDaniel T, DeMagistris M, Callan C, Huxlin KR, 2018. Corneal myofibroblasts inhibit regenerating nerves during wound healing. Scientific reports 8, 12945.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6113331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30154512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jester JV, Petroll WM, Cavanagh HD, 1999. Corneal stromal wound healing in refractive surgery: the role of myofibroblasts. Progress in retinal and eye research 18, 311&#8211;356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10192516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones K, Choi J-H, Sponsel WE, Gray W, Groth SL, Glickman RD, Lund BJ, Reilly MA, 2016. Low-level primary blast causes acute ocular trauma in rabbits. Journal of neurotrauma 33, 1194&#8211;1201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26393900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kato T, Nakayasu K, Hosoda Y, Watanabe Y, Kanai A, 1999. Corneal wound healing following laser in situ keratomileusis (LASIK): a histopathological study in rabbits. The British journal of ophthalmology 83, 1302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1722864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10535863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kauffmann T, Bodanowitz S, Hesse L, Kroll P, 1996. Corneal reinnervation after photorefractive keratectomy and laser in situ keratomileusis: an in vivo study with a confocal videomicroscope. German journal of ophthalmology 5, 508&#8211;512.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9479547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Ashraf MF, Bekoe NA, Stark WJ, Chan C-C, O&#8217;Brien TPJG s.a.f.c., ophthalmology, e., 2000. The role of apoptosis in the early corneal wound healing after excimer laser keratectomy in the rat. 238, 853&#8211;860.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11127573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin A, Guo X, Inman RD, Sivak JM, 2015. Ocular inflammation in HLA-B27 transgenic mice reveals a potential role for MHC class I in corneal immune privilege. Molecular vision 21, 131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4323692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25684978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu YC, Jung ASJ, Chin JY, Yang LWY, Mehta JS, 2020. Cross-sectional Study on Corneal Denervation in Contralateral Eyes Following SMILE Versus LASIK. Journal of Refractive Surgery 36, 653&#8211;660.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33034357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lundberg B, Jonsson M, Behndig A, 2005. Postoperative corneal swelling correlates strongly to corneal endothelial cell loss after phacoemulsification cataract surgery. American journal of ophthalmology 139, 1035&#8211;1041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15953433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma K, Yan N, Huang Y, Cao G, Deng J, Deng Y, 2014. Effects of nerve growth factor on nerve regeneration after corneal nerve damage. International journal of clinical and experimental medicine 7, 4584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4276247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25550989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marfurt CF, Cox J, Deek S, Dvorscak L, 2010. Anatomy of the human corneal innervation. Experimental eye research 90, 478&#8211;492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20036654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medeiros CS, Marino GK, Lassance L, Thangavadivel S, Santhiago MR, Wilson SE, 2018. The impact of photorefractive keratectomy and mitomycin C on corneal nerves and their regeneration. Journal of Refractive Surgery 34, 790&#8211;798.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6360090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30540361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meltendorf C, Burbach GJ, B&#252;hren J, Bug R, Ohrloff C, Deller T, 2007. Corneal femtosecond laser keratotomy results in isolated stromal injury and favorable wound-healing response. Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 48, 2068&#8211;2075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17460262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyamoto T, Saika S, Yamanaka A, Kawashima Y, Suzuki Y, Ohnishi Y, 2003. Wound healing in rabbit corneas after photorefractive keratectomy and laser in situ keratomileusis. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 29, 153&#8211;158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12551683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed-Noriega K, Riau AK, Lwin NC, Chaurasia SS, Tan DT, Mehta JS, 2014. Early corneal nerve damage and recovery following small incision lenticule extraction (SMILE) and laser in situ keratomileusis (LASIK). Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 55, 1823&#8211;1834.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24569584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohan RR, Hutcheon AE, Choi R, Hong J, Lee J, Mohan RR, Ambr&#243;sio R, Zieske JD, Wilson SE, 2003. Apoptosis, necrosis, proliferation, and myofibroblast generation in the stroma following LASIK and PRK. Experimental eye research 76, 71&#8211;87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12589777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakamura K, Kurosaka D, Bissen-Miyajima H, Tsubota K, 2001. Intact corneal epithelium is essential for the prevention of stromal haze after laser assisted in situ keratomileusis. British journal of ophthalmology 85, 209&#8211;213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1723865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11159488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Netto MV, Mohan RR, Ambr&#243;sio R Jr, Hutcheon AE, Zieske JD, Wilson SE, 2005. Wound healing in the cornea: a review of refractive surgery complications and new prospects for therapy. Cornea 24, 509&#8211;522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15968154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Netto MV, Mohan RR, Medeiros FW, Dupps WJ Jr, Sinha S, Krueger RR, Stapleton WM, Rayborn M, Suto C, Wilson SE, 2007. Femtosecond laser and microkeratome corneal flaps: comparison of stromal wound healing and inflammation. Journal of refractive surgery (Thorofare, NJ: 1995) 23, 667.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2698458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17912936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nien CJ, Flynn KJ, Chang M, Brown D, Jester JV, 2011. Reducing peak corneal haze after photorefractive keratectomy in rabbits: prednisolone acetate 1.00% versus cyclosporine A 0.05%. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 37, 937&#8211;944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3085941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21406325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel SV, Erie JC, 2003. Aberrant regeneration of corneal nerves after laser in situ keratomileusis. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 29, 387&#8211;389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12648654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng MY, Hannan S, Teenan D, Schallhorn SJ, Schallhorn JM, 2018. Monovision LASIK in emmetropic presbyopic patients. Clinical Ophthalmology (Auckland, NZ) 12, 1665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6130303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30233129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pettit GH, Ediger MN, Weiblinger RP, 1995. Excimer laser ablation of the cornea. Optical Engineering 34, 661&#8211;667.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao G, Shaw E, Arthur E, Aquavella J, 1979. Endothelial cell morphology and corneal deturgescence. Annals of ophthalmology 11, 885&#8211;899.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">496182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raviv T, Majmudar PA, Dennis RF, Epstein RJ, 2000. Mitomycin-C for post-PRK corneal haze. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 26, 1105&#8211;1106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11041724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salom&#227;o MQ, Ambr&#243;sio R, Wilson SE, 2009. Dry eye associated with laser in situ keratomileusis: mechanical microkeratome versus femtosecond laser. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 35, 1756&#8211;1760.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4133944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19781472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savage DE, Brooks DR, DeMagistris M, Xu L, MacRae S, Ellis JD, Knox WH, Huxlin KR, 2014. First demonstration of ocular refractive change using blue-iris in live cats. Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 55, 4603.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4112606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24985471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaheen BS, Bakir M, Jain S, 2014. Corneal nerves in health and disease. Survey of ophthalmology 59, 263&#8211;285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4004679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24461367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shortt AJ, Allan BD, Evans JR, 2013. Laser&#8208;assisted in&#8208;situ keratomileusis (LASIK) versus photorefractive keratectomy (PRK) for myopia. Cochrane Database of systematic reviews.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23440799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spadea L, Giammaria D, Trabucco P, 2016. Corneal wound healing after laser vision correction. British Journal of Ophthalmology 100, 28&#8211;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26405102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres LF, Sancho C, Tan B, Padilla K, Schanzlin DJ, Chayet AS, 2007. Early postoperative pain following Epi-LASIK and photorefractive keratectomy: a prospective, comparative, bilateral study. Journal of refractive surgery 23, 126&#8211;132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17326351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torricelli AA, Santhanam A, Wu J, Singh V, Wilson SE, 2016. The corneal fibrosis response to epithelial&#8211;stromal injury. Experimental eye research 142, 110&#8211;118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4683352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26675407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waring III GO, Bourne WM, Edelhauser HF, Kenyon KR, 1982. The corneal endothelium: normal and pathologic structure and function. Ophthalmology 89, 531&#8211;590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7122038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watsky MA, 1995. Keratocyte gap junctional communication in normal and wounded rabbit corneas and human corneas. Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 36, 2568&#8211;2576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7499079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, 1997. Molecular cell biology for the refractive corneal surgeon: programmed cell death and wound healing. Journal of Refractive Surgery 13, 171.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9109075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, 2000. Role of apoptosis in wound healing in the cornea. Cornea 19, S7&#8211;S12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10832715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, 2020a. Biology of keratorefractive surgery-PRK, PTK, LASIK, SMILE, inlays and other refractive procedures. Experimental Eye Research 198, 108136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7508965</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32653492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, 2020b. Corneal wound healing. Experimental eye research 197, 108089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7483425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32553485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, Kim W-J, 1998. Keratocyte apoptosis: implications on corneal wound healing, tissue organization, and disease. Investigative Ophthalmology and Visual Science 39, 220&#8211;226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9477978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, Mohan RR, Mohan RR, Ambr&#243;sio R, Hong J, Lee J, 2001. The Corneal Wound Healing Response:: Cytokine-mediated Interaction of the Epithelium, Stroma, and Inflammatory Cells. Progress in retinal and eye research 20, 625&#8211;637.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11470453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wozniak KT, Elkins N, Brooks DR, Savage DE, MacRae S, Ellis JD, Knox WH, Huxlin KR, 2017. Contrasting cellular damage after Blue-IRIS and Femto-LASIK in cat cornea. Experimental eye research 165, 20&#8211;28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5705398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28866013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wozniak KT, Germer TA, Butler SC, Brooks DR, Huxlin KR, Ellis JD, 2018. Scattering properties of ultrafast laser-induced refractive index shaping lenticular structures in hydrogels, Frontiers in Ultrafast Optics: Biomedical, Scientific, and Industrial Applications XVIII. International Society for Optics and Photonics, p. 1052205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Knox WH, Huxlin KR, 2011. Exogenous and endogenous two-photon absorption for Intra-tissue Refractive Index Shaping (IRIS) in live corneal tissue [Invited]. Optical Materials Express 1, 1159&#8211;1164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamada N, Matsuda R, Morishige N, Yanai R, Chikama T, Nishida T, Ishimitsu T, Kamiya A, 2008. Open clinical study of eye-drops containing tetrapeptides derived from substance P and insulin-like growth factor-1 for treatment of persistent corneal epithelial defects associated with neurotrophic keratopathy. British Journal of Ophthalmology 92, 896&#8211;900.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18511539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu D, Brown EB, Huxlin KR, Knox WH, 2019. Tissue effects of intra-tissue refractive index shaping (IRIS): insights from two-photon autofluorescence and second harmonic generation microscopy. Biomedical optics express 10, 855&#8211;867.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6377903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30800519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheleznyak L, Butler SC, Cox IG, Huxlin KR, Ellis JD, Knox W, Waltz K, Vukich JA, Quesada G, Quesada R, 2019. First-in-human laser-induced refractive index change (LIRIC) treatment of the cornea. Investigative Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Science 60, 5079&#8211;5079.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>