<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2019//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_190101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Owner="NLM" Status="MEDLINE"><PMID Version="1">33864783</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-0007</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>207</Volume><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Experimental eye research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Exp Eye Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Temporal evolution of the biological response to laser-induced refractive index change (LIRIC) in rabbit corneas.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>108579</StartPage><MedlinePgn>108579</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.exer.2021.108579</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0014-4835(21)00144-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Laser-induced refractive index change (LIRIC) is a new, non-incisional, non-ablative, femtosecond photo-modification technique being developed for vision correction in humans. Prior, exvivo studies showed intra-tissue refractive index change to induce minimal cell death, restricted to the laser focal zone in the corneal stroma, and with no observable damage to the epithelium or endothelium. Here, we used live rabbits to ascertain longer-term consequences of LIRIC in vivo. Specifically, we assessed cell death, fibrosis, corneal nerve distribution, endothelial cell density, and corneal structure for up to 3 months after LIRIC. A +2.5 D gradient-index LIRIC Fresnel lens was inscribed inside 20 applanated corneas of Dutch Belted rabbits, over a circular region of the mid-stroma measuring 4.5&#160;mm in diameter. Twelve additional rabbit eyes were used as applanation-only controls to differentiate the effects of laser treatment and suction applanation on biological and structural parameters. In vivo optical measurements were performed pre-operatively, then immediately, 2, 4, and 12 weeks after the procedure, to measure endothelial cell density and changes in corneal structure. Groups of four rabbits were sacrificed at 4&#160;hours, 2, 4, and 12 weeks after LIRIC for histological determinations; the TUNEL assay was used to evaluate cell death, H&amp;E staining was used to assess inflammatory infiltration, and immunostaining for &#945;-smooth muscle actin (&#945;-SMA) and &#946;III tubulin (Tuj-1) was performed to assess myofibroblast differentiation and corneal nerve distribution, respectively. Consistent with prior ex vivo data, only minimal cell death was observed in the laser focal zone, with TUNEL-positive cells restricted to the stromal region of refractive index change 4&#160;h after LIRIC. No TUNEL-positive cells were evident anywhere in the cornea 2, 4, or 12 weeks after LIRIC. Applanation-only corneas were completely TUNEL-negative. Neither LIRIC-treated nor applanation-only eyes exhibited &#945;-SMA-positive staining or altered corneal nerve distributions at any of the time points examined. In vivo confocal imaging revealed normal endothelial cell densities in all eyes (whether LIRIC-treated or applanation-only) at all time points. Optical coherence tomography showed suction applanation to cause a temporary decrease in central corneal thickness, which returned to normal within 4&#160;h. Corneas into which LIRIC Fresnel lenses were written while applanated did not undergo major structural or shape changes beyond the temporary thinning already described for suction applanation. The present findings suggest that LIRIC patterns, which generated a clinically-relevant refractive correction in the mid-stromal region of live rabbit corneas, induced little-to-no disruption to corneal structure and biology for 3 months after the procedure. This affirms the relative safety of LIRIC and predicts that compared to traditional laser vision correction surgeries, common post-operative complications such as dry eye, haze, or patient discomfort may be entirely avoided.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#169; 2021 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wozniak</LastName><ForeName>Kaitlin T</ForeName><Initials>KT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Institute of Optics, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Center for Visual Science, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Flaum Eye Institute, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14642, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Butler</LastName><ForeName>Sam C</ForeName><Initials>SC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clerio Vision Inc., Rochester, NY, 14618, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Xu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Flaum Eye Institute, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14642, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ellis</LastName><ForeName>Jonathan D</ForeName><Initials>JD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clerio Vision Inc., Rochester, NY, 14618, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Knox</LastName><ForeName>Wayne H</ForeName><Initials>WH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Institute of Optics, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Center for Visual Science, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huxlin</LastName><ForeName>Krystel R</ForeName><Initials>KR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Institute of Optics, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Center for Visual Science, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14627, USA; The Flaum Eye Institute, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY, 14642, USA. Electronic address: khuxlin@ur.rochester.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P30 EY001319</GrantID><Acronym>EY</Acronym><Agency>NEI NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 EY015836</GrantID><Acronym>EY</Acronym><Agency>NEI NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013486">Research Support, U.S. Gov't, Non-P.H.S.</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Exp Eye Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370707</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0014-4835</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D000818">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D002452">Cell Count</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D016923">Cell Death</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D003315">Cornea</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000294">innervation</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D003319">Corneal Stroma</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000503">physiopathology</QualifierName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000601">surgery</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D048988">Corneal Surgery, Laser</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000379">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D004728">Endothelium, Corneal</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000473">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D005260">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D005355">Fibrosis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D018613">Microscopy, Confocal</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D009882">Ophthalmic Nerve</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000502">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D011817">Rabbits</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D012029">Refraction, Ocular</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000502">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D041623">Tomography, Optical Coherence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D014792">Visual Acuity</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000502">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D014945">Wound Healing</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="Q000502">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Corneal endothelial cells</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Corneal nerves</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Myofibroblasts</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Refractive surgery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Stroma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TUNEL</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wound healing</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2020</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2021</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33864783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1697484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8187327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.exer.2021.108579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0014-4835(21)00144-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ambr&#243;sio R Jr, Tervo T, Wilson SE, 2008. LASIK-associated dry eye and neurotrophic epitheliopathy: pathophysiology and strategies for prevention and treatment. Journal of refractive surgery 24, 396&#8211;407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18500091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aron-Rosa DS, Boulnoy JL, Carr&#233; F, Delacour J, Gross M, Lacour M, Olivo JC, Timsit JC, 1986. Excimer laser surgery of the cornea: qualitative and quantitative aspects of photoablation according to the energy density. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 12, 27&#8211;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3958947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baum J, Maurice D, McCarey B, 1984. The active and passive transport of water across the corneal endothelium. Experimental eye research 39, 335&#8211;342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6499954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belmonte C, Acosta MC, Gallar J, 2004. Neural basis of sensation in intact and injured corneas. Experimental eye research 78, 513&#8211;525.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15106930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks DR, Brown NS, Savage DE, Wang C, Knox WH, Ellis JD, 2014. Precision large field scanning system for high numerical aperture lenses and application to femtosecond micromachining of ophthalmic materials. Review of Scientific Instruments 85, 065107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24985852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>B&#252;hren J, Nagy L, Swanton JN, Kenner S, MacRae S, Phipps RP, Huxlin KR, 2009. Optical effects of anti-TGF&#946; treatment after photorefractive keratectomy in a cat model. Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 50, 634&#8211;643.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2753416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18952913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campos M, Szerenyi K, Lee M, McDonnell JM, Lopez PF, McDonnell PJ, 1994. Keratocyte loss after corneal deepithelialization in primates and rabbits. Archives of ophthalmology 112, 254&#8211;260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8311779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan A, Manche EE, 2011. Effect of preoperative pupil size on quality of vision after wavefront-guided LASIK. Ophthalmology 118, 736&#8211;741.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21093922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding L, Blackwell R, K&#252;nzler JF, Knox WH, 2006. Large refractive index change in silicone-based and non-silicone-based hydrogel polymers induced by femtosecond laser micro-machining. Optics express 14, 11901&#8211;11909.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19529613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doughty MJ, Cullen AP, 1990. Long&#8208;term effects of a single dose of ultraviolet&#8208;B on albino rabbit cornea&#8211;II. Deturgescence and fluid pump assessed in vitro. Photochemistry and photobiology 51, 439&#8211;449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2343062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erie JC, McLaren JW, Hodge DO, Bourne WM, 2005. Recovery of corneal subbasal nerve density after PRK and LASIK. American journal of ophthalmology 140, 1059&#8211;1064. e1051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16376651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espana E, Ti S, Grueterich M, Touhami A, Tseng S, 2003. Corneal stromal changes following reconstruction by ex vivo expanded limbal epithelial cells in rabbits with total limbal stem cell deficiency. British journal of ophthalmology 87, 1509&#8211;1514.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1920578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14660463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan-Paul NI, Li J, Miller JS, Florakis GJ, 2002. Night vision disturbances after corneal refractive surgery. Survey of ophthalmology 47, 533&#8211;546.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12504738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandara-Montano GA, Ivansky A, Savage DE, Ellis JD, Knox WH, 2015. Femtosecond laser writing of freeform gradient index microlenses in hydrogel-based contact lenses. Optical Materials Express 5, 2257&#8211;2271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandara-Montano GA, Stoy V, Dudi&#269; M, Petr&#225;k V, Ha&#353;kovcov&#225; K, Knox WH, 2017. Large optical phase shifts in hydrogels written with femtosecond laser pulses: elucidating the role of localized water concentration changes. Optical Materials Express 7, 3162&#8211;3180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao J, Gelber-Schwalb TA, Addeo JV, Stern ME, 1997. Apoptosis in the rabbit cornea after photorefractive keratectomy. Cornea 16, 200&#8211;208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9071534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He J, Bazan NG, Bazan HE, 2010. Mapping the entire human corneal nerve architecture. Experimental eye research 91, 513&#8211;523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2939211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20650270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helena MC, Baerveldt F, Kim W-J, Wilson SE, 1998. Keratocyte apoptosis after corneal surgery. Investigative Ophthalmology and Visual Science 39, 276&#8211;283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9477983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hindman HB, DeMagistris M, Callan C, McDaniel T, Bubel T, Huxlin KR, 2019. Impact of topical anti-fibrotics on corneal nerve regeneration in vivo. Experimental eye research 181, 49&#8211;60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6443430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30660507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huxlin KR, Hindman HB, Jeon K-I, B&#252;hren J, MacRae S, DeMagistris M, Ciufo D, Sime PJ, Phipps RP, 2013. Topical rosiglitazone is an effective anti-scarring agent in the cornea. PloS one 8, e70785.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3733781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23940641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeon K-I, Hindman HB, Bubel T, McDaniel T, DeMagistris M, Callan C, Huxlin KR, 2018. Corneal myofibroblasts inhibit regenerating nerves during wound healing. Scientific reports 8, 12945.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6113331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30154512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jester JV, Petroll WM, Cavanagh HD, 1999. Corneal stromal wound healing in refractive surgery: the role of myofibroblasts. Progress in retinal and eye research 18, 311&#8211;356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10192516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones K, Choi J-H, Sponsel WE, Gray W, Groth SL, Glickman RD, Lund BJ, Reilly MA, 2016. Low-level primary blast causes acute ocular trauma in rabbits. Journal of neurotrauma 33, 1194&#8211;1201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26393900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kato T, Nakayasu K, Hosoda Y, Watanabe Y, Kanai A, 1999. Corneal wound healing following laser in situ keratomileusis (LASIK): a histopathological study in rabbits. The British journal of ophthalmology 83, 1302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1722864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10535863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kauffmann T, Bodanowitz S, Hesse L, Kroll P, 1996. Corneal reinnervation after photorefractive keratectomy and laser in situ keratomileusis: an in vivo study with a confocal videomicroscope. German journal of ophthalmology 5, 508&#8211;512.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9479547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Ashraf MF, Bekoe NA, Stark WJ, Chan C-C, O&#8217;Brien TPJG s.a.f.c., ophthalmology, e., 2000. The role of apoptosis in the early corneal wound healing after excimer laser keratectomy in the rat. 238, 853&#8211;860.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11127573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin A, Guo X, Inman RD, Sivak JM, 2015. Ocular inflammation in HLA-B27 transgenic mice reveals a potential role for MHC class I in corneal immune privilege. Molecular vision 21, 131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4323692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25684978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu YC, Jung ASJ, Chin JY, Yang LWY, Mehta JS, 2020. Cross-sectional Study on Corneal Denervation in Contralateral Eyes Following SMILE Versus LASIK. Journal of Refractive Surgery 36, 653&#8211;660.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33034357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lundberg B, Jonsson M, Behndig A, 2005. Postoperative corneal swelling correlates strongly to corneal endothelial cell loss after phacoemulsification cataract surgery. American journal of ophthalmology 139, 1035&#8211;1041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15953433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma K, Yan N, Huang Y, Cao G, Deng J, Deng Y, 2014. Effects of nerve growth factor on nerve regeneration after corneal nerve damage. International journal of clinical and experimental medicine 7, 4584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4276247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25550989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marfurt CF, Cox J, Deek S, Dvorscak L, 2010. Anatomy of the human corneal innervation. Experimental eye research 90, 478&#8211;492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20036654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medeiros CS, Marino GK, Lassance L, Thangavadivel S, Santhiago MR, Wilson SE, 2018. The impact of photorefractive keratectomy and mitomycin C on corneal nerves and their regeneration. Journal of Refractive Surgery 34, 790&#8211;798.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6360090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30540361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meltendorf C, Burbach GJ, B&#252;hren J, Bug R, Ohrloff C, Deller T, 2007. Corneal femtosecond laser keratotomy results in isolated stromal injury and favorable wound-healing response. Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 48, 2068&#8211;2075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17460262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyamoto T, Saika S, Yamanaka A, Kawashima Y, Suzuki Y, Ohnishi Y, 2003. Wound healing in rabbit corneas after photorefractive keratectomy and laser in situ keratomileusis. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 29, 153&#8211;158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12551683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed-Noriega K, Riau AK, Lwin NC, Chaurasia SS, Tan DT, Mehta JS, 2014. Early corneal nerve damage and recovery following small incision lenticule extraction (SMILE) and laser in situ keratomileusis (LASIK). Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 55, 1823&#8211;1834.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24569584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohan RR, Hutcheon AE, Choi R, Hong J, Lee J, Mohan RR, Ambr&#243;sio R, Zieske JD, Wilson SE, 2003. Apoptosis, necrosis, proliferation, and myofibroblast generation in the stroma following LASIK and PRK. Experimental eye research 76, 71&#8211;87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12589777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakamura K, Kurosaka D, Bissen-Miyajima H, Tsubota K, 2001. Intact corneal epithelium is essential for the prevention of stromal haze after laser assisted in situ keratomileusis. British journal of ophthalmology 85, 209&#8211;213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1723865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11159488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Netto MV, Mohan RR, Ambr&#243;sio R Jr, Hutcheon AE, Zieske JD, Wilson SE, 2005. Wound healing in the cornea: a review of refractive surgery complications and new prospects for therapy. Cornea 24, 509&#8211;522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15968154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Netto MV, Mohan RR, Medeiros FW, Dupps WJ Jr, Sinha S, Krueger RR, Stapleton WM, Rayborn M, Suto C, Wilson SE, 2007. Femtosecond laser and microkeratome corneal flaps: comparison of stromal wound healing and inflammation. Journal of refractive surgery (Thorofare, NJ: 1995) 23, 667.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2698458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17912936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nien CJ, Flynn KJ, Chang M, Brown D, Jester JV, 2011. Reducing peak corneal haze after photorefractive keratectomy in rabbits: prednisolone acetate 1.00% versus cyclosporine A 0.05%. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 37, 937&#8211;944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3085941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21406325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel SV, Erie JC, 2003. Aberrant regeneration of corneal nerves after laser in situ keratomileusis. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 29, 387&#8211;389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12648654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng MY, Hannan S, Teenan D, Schallhorn SJ, Schallhorn JM, 2018. Monovision LASIK in emmetropic presbyopic patients. Clinical Ophthalmology (Auckland, NZ) 12, 1665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6130303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30233129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pettit GH, Ediger MN, Weiblinger RP, 1995. Excimer laser ablation of the cornea. Optical Engineering 34, 661&#8211;667.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao G, Shaw E, Arthur E, Aquavella J, 1979. Endothelial cell morphology and corneal deturgescence. Annals of ophthalmology 11, 885&#8211;899.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">496182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raviv T, Majmudar PA, Dennis RF, Epstein RJ, 2000. Mitomycin-C for post-PRK corneal haze. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 26, 1105&#8211;1106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11041724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salom&#227;o MQ, Ambr&#243;sio R, Wilson SE, 2009. Dry eye associated with laser in situ keratomileusis: mechanical microkeratome versus femtosecond laser. Journal of Cataract &amp; Refractive Surgery 35, 1756&#8211;1760.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4133944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19781472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savage DE, Brooks DR, DeMagistris M, Xu L, MacRae S, Ellis JD, Knox WH, Huxlin KR, 2014. First demonstration of ocular refractive change using blue-iris in live cats. Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 55, 4603.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4112606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24985471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaheen BS, Bakir M, Jain S, 2014. Corneal nerves in health and disease. Survey of ophthalmology 59, 263&#8211;285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4004679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24461367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shortt AJ, Allan BD, Evans JR, 2013. Laser&#8208;assisted in&#8208;situ keratomileusis (LASIK) versus photorefractive keratectomy (PRK) for myopia. Cochrane Database of systematic reviews.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23440799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spadea L, Giammaria D, Trabucco P, 2016. Corneal wound healing after laser vision correction. British Journal of Ophthalmology 100, 28&#8211;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26405102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres LF, Sancho C, Tan B, Padilla K, Schanzlin DJ, Chayet AS, 2007. Early postoperative pain following Epi-LASIK and photorefractive keratectomy: a prospective, comparative, bilateral study. Journal of refractive surgery 23, 126&#8211;132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17326351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torricelli AA, Santhanam A, Wu J, Singh V, Wilson SE, 2016. The corneal fibrosis response to epithelial&#8211;stromal injury. Experimental eye research 142, 110&#8211;118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4683352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26675407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waring III GO, Bourne WM, Edelhauser HF, Kenyon KR, 1982. The corneal endothelium: normal and pathologic structure and function. Ophthalmology 89, 531&#8211;590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7122038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watsky MA, 1995. Keratocyte gap junctional communication in normal and wounded rabbit corneas and human corneas. Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science 36, 2568&#8211;2576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7499079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, 1997. Molecular cell biology for the refractive corneal surgeon: programmed cell death and wound healing. Journal of Refractive Surgery 13, 171.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9109075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, 2000. Role of apoptosis in wound healing in the cornea. Cornea 19, S7&#8211;S12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10832715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, 2020a. Biology of keratorefractive surgery-PRK, PTK, LASIK, SMILE, inlays and other refractive procedures. Experimental Eye Research 198, 108136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7508965</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32653492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, 2020b. Corneal wound healing. Experimental eye research 197, 108089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7483425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32553485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, Kim W-J, 1998. Keratocyte apoptosis: implications on corneal wound healing, tissue organization, and disease. Investigative Ophthalmology and Visual Science 39, 220&#8211;226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9477978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SE, Mohan RR, Mohan RR, Ambr&#243;sio R, Hong J, Lee J, 2001. The Corneal Wound Healing Response:: Cytokine-mediated Interaction of the Epithelium, Stroma, and Inflammatory Cells. Progress in retinal and eye research 20, 625&#8211;637.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11470453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wozniak KT, Elkins N, Brooks DR, Savage DE, MacRae S, Ellis JD, Knox WH, Huxlin KR, 2017. Contrasting cellular damage after Blue-IRIS and Femto-LASIK in cat cornea. Experimental eye research 165, 20&#8211;28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5705398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28866013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wozniak KT, Germer TA, Butler SC, Brooks DR, Huxlin KR, Ellis JD, 2018. Scattering properties of ultrafast laser-induced refractive index shaping lenticular structures in hydrogels, Frontiers in Ultrafast Optics: Biomedical, Scientific, and Industrial Applications XVIII. International Society for Optics and Photonics, p. 1052205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Knox WH, Huxlin KR, 2011. Exogenous and endogenous two-photon absorption for Intra-tissue Refractive Index Shaping (IRIS) in live corneal tissue [Invited]. Optical Materials Express 1, 1159&#8211;1164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamada N, Matsuda R, Morishige N, Yanai R, Chikama T, Nishida T, Ishimitsu T, Kamiya A, 2008. Open clinical study of eye-drops containing tetrapeptides derived from substance P and insulin-like growth factor-1 for treatment of persistent corneal epithelial defects associated with neurotrophic keratopathy. British Journal of Ophthalmology 92, 896&#8211;900.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18511539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu D, Brown EB, Huxlin KR, Knox WH, 2019. Tissue effects of intra-tissue refractive index shaping (IRIS): insights from two-photon autofluorescence and second harmonic generation microscopy. Biomedical optics express 10, 855&#8211;867.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6377903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30800519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheleznyak L, Butler SC, Cox IG, Huxlin KR, Ellis JD, Knox W, Waltz K, Vukich JA, Quesada G, Quesada R, 2019. First-in-human laser-induced refractive index change (LIRIC) treatment of the cornea. Investigative Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Science 60, 5079&#8211;5079.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle><PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Owner="NLM" Status="MEDLINE"><PMID Version="1">20237243</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2011</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1460-2199</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>20</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cerebral cortex (New York, N.Y. : 1991)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cereb Cortex</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Longitudinal analysis of neural network development in preterm infants.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2852</StartPage><EndPage>2862</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2852-62</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/cercor/bhq035</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Application of resting state functional connectivity magnetic resonance imaging (fcMRI) to the study of prematurely born infants enables assessment of the earliest forms of cerebral connectivity and characterization of its early development in the human brain. We obtained 90 longitudinal fcMRI data sets from a cohort of preterm infants aged from 26 weeks postmenstrual age (PMA) through term equivalent age at PMA-specific time points. Utilizing seed-based correlation analysis, we identified resting state networks involving varied cortical regions, the thalamus, and cerebellum. Identified networks demonstrated a regionally variable age-specific pattern of development, with more mature forms consisting of localized interhemispheric connections between homotopic counterparts. Anatomical distance was found to play a critical role in the rate of connection development. Prominent differences were noted between networks identified in term control versus premature infants at term equivalent, including in the thalamocortical connections critical for neurodevelopment. Putative precursors of the default mode network were detected in term control infants but were not identified in preterm infants, including those at term equivalent. Identified patterns of network maturation reflect the intricate relationship of structural and functional processes present throughout this important developmental period and are consistent with prior investigations of neurodevelopment in this population.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smyser</LastName><ForeName>Christopher D</ForeName><Initials>CD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Division of Pediatric Neurology, Washington University School ofMedicine, 660 South Euclid Avenue, Saint Louis, MO 63110-1093, USA. smyserc@neuro.wustl.edu</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Inder</LastName><ForeName>Terrie E</ForeName><Initials>TE</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shimony</LastName><ForeName>Joshua S</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hill</LastName><ForeName>Jason E</ForeName><Initials>JE</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Degnan</LastName><ForeName>Andrew J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Snyder</LastName><ForeName>Abraham Z</ForeName><Initials>AZ</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Neil</LastName><ForeName>Jeffrey J</ForeName><Initials>JJ</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 HD057098</GrantID><Acronym>HD</Acronym><Agency>NICHD NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>K23 HD053212</GrantID><Acronym>HD</Acronym><Agency>NICHD NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>P30 NS048056</GrantID><Acronym>NS</Acronym><Agency>NINDS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 HD05709801</GrantID><Acronym>HD</Acronym><Agency>NICHD NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2010</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cereb Cortex</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9110718</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1047-3211</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D001921">Brain</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000254">growth &amp; development</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D005260">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D006801">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D007090">Image Interpretation, Computer-Assisted</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D007231">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000254">growth &amp; development</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D008279">Magnetic Resonance Imaging</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D008297">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D009415">Nerve Net</DescriptorName><QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="Q000254">growth &amp; development</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="Y" UI="D055495">Neurogenesis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D011247">Pregnancy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName MajorTopicYN="N" UI="D047928">Premature Birth</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2011</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20237243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2978240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhq035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">bhq035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Anjari M, Srinivasan L, Allsop JM, Hajnal JV, Rutherford MA, Edwards AD, Counsell SJ. Diffusion tensor imaging with tract-based spatial statistics reveals local white matter abnormalities in preterm infants. Neuroimage. 2007;35:1021&#8211;1027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17344066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bassi L, Ricci D, Volzone A, Allsop JM, Srinivasan L, Pai A, Ribes C, Ramenghi LA, Mercuri E, Mosca F, et al. Probabilistic diffusion tractography of the optic radiations and visual function in preterm infants at term equivalent age. Brain. 2008;131:573&#8211;582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18222994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beckmann CF, DeLuca M, Devlin JT, Smith SM. Investigations into resting-state connectivity using independent component analysis. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 2005;360:1001&#8211;1013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1854918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16087444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biswal B, Yetkin FZ, Haughton VM, Hyde JS. Functional connectivity in the motor cortex of resting human brain using echo-planar MRI. Magn Reson Med. 1995;34:537&#8211;541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8524021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Born AP, Miranda MJ, Rostrup E, Toft PB, Peitersen B, Larsson HB, Lou HC. Functional magnetic resonance imaging of the normal and abnormal visual system in early life. Neuropediatrics. 2000;31:24&#8211;32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10774992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourgeois JP, Jastreboff PJ, Rakic P. Synaptogenesis in visual cortex of normal and preterm monkeys: evidence for intrinsic regulation of synaptic overproduction. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1989;86:4297&#8211;4301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC287439</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2726773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burgund ED, Kang HC, Kelly JE, Buckner RL, Snyder AZ, Petersen SE, Schlaggar BL. The feasibility of a common stereotactic space for children and adults in fMRI studies of development. Neuroimage. 2002;17:184&#8211;200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12482076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chugani HT. A critical period of brain development: studies of cerebral glucose utilization with PET. Prev Med. 1998;27:184&#8211;188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9578992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen AL, Fair DA, Dosenbach NU, Miezin FM, Dierker D, Van Essen DC, Schlaggar BL, Petersen SE. Defining functional areas in individual human brains using resting functional connectivity MRI. Neuroimage. 2008;41:45&#8211;57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2705206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18367410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Counsell SJ, Dyet LE, Larkman DJ, Nunes RG, Boardman JP, Allsop JM, Fitzpatrick J, Srinivasan L, Cowan FM, Hajnal JV, et al. Thalamo-cortical connectivity in children born preterm mapped using probabilistic magnetic resonance tractography. Neuroimage. 2007;34:896&#8211;904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17174575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damoiseaux JS, Greicius MD. Greater than the sum of its parts: a review of studies combining structural connectivity and resting-state functional connectivity. Brain Struct Funct. 2009;213:525&#8211;533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19565262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damoiseaux JS, Rombouts SA, Barkhof F, Scheltens P, Stam CJ, Smith SM, Beckmann CF. Consistent resting-state networks across healthy subjects. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2006;103:13848&#8211;13853.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1564249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16945915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doria V, Beckmann CF, Rees G, Nunes RG, Merchant N, Counsell S, Edwards D. Spontaneous brain activity in infants from 33 weeks gestational age [abstract] Washington (DC): Society for Neuroscience; 2008. Program No. 787.13/SS50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dosenbach NU, Fair DA, Miezin FM, Cohen AL, Wenger KK, Dosenbach RA, Fox MD, Snyder AZ, Vincent JL, Raichle ME, et al. Distinct brain networks for adaptive and stable task control in humans. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007;104:11073&#8211;11078.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1904171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17576922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erberich SG, Panigrahy A, Friedlich P, Seri I, Nelson MD, Gilles F. Somatosensory lateralization in the newborn brain. Neuroimage. 2006;29:155&#8211;161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16112875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fair DA, Cohen AL, Dosenbach NU, Church JA, Miezin FM, Barch DM, Raichle ME, Petersen SE, Schlaggar BL. The maturing architecture of the brain&#8217;s default network. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2008;105:4028&#8211;4032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2268790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18322013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fair DA, Dosenbach NU, Church JA, Cohen AL, Brahmbhatt S, Miezin FM, Barch DM, Raichle ME, Petersen SE, Schlaggar BL. Development of distinct control networks through segregation and integration. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007;104:13507&#8211;13512.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1940033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17679691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fair DA, Schlaggar BL, Cohen AL, Miezin FM, Dosenbach NU, Wenger KK, Fox MD, Snyder AZ, Raichle ME, Petersen SE. A method for using blocked and event-related fMRI data to study &#8220;resting state&#8221; functional connectivity. Neuroimage. 2007;35:396&#8211;405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2563954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17239622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox MD, Raichle ME. Spontaneous fluctuations in brain activity observed with functional magnetic resonance imaging. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2007;8:700&#8211;711.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17704812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox MD, Snyder AZ, Vincent JL, Corbetta M, Van Essen DC, Raichle ME. The human brain is intrinsically organized into dynamic, anticorrelated functional networks. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005;102:9673&#8211;9678.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1157105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15976020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fransson P, Skiold B, Engstrom M, Hallberg B, Mosskin M, Aden U, Lagercrantz H, Blennow M. Spontaneous brain activity in the newborn brain during natural sleep&#8212;an fMRI study in infants born at full term. Pediatr Res. 2009;66:301&#8211;305.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19531974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fransson P, Skiold B, Horsch S, Nordell A, Blennow M, Lagercrantz H, Aden U. Resting-state networks in the infant brain. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007;104:15531&#8211;15536.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2000516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17878310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao W, Zhu H, Giovanello KS, Smith JK, Shen D, Gilmore JH, Lin W. Evidence on the emergence of the brain&#8217;s default network from 2-week-old to 2-year-old healthy pediatric subjects. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2009;106:6790&#8211;6795.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2672537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19351894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greicius MD, Kiviniemi V, Tervonen O, Vainionp&#228;&#228; V, Alahuhta S, Reiss AL, Menon V. Persistent default-mode network connectivity during light sedation. Hum Brain Mapp. 2008;29:839&#8211;847.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2580760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18219620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heep A, Scheef L, Jankowski J, Born M, Zimmermann N, Sival D, Bos A, Gieseke J, Bartmann P, Schild H, et al. Functional magnetic resonance imaging of the sensorimotor system in preterm infants. Pediatrics. 2009;123:294&#8211;300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19117895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honey CJ, Kotter R, Breakspear M, Sporns O. Network structure of cerebral cortex shapes functional connectivity on multiple time scales. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007;104:10240&#8211;10245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1891224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17548818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horovitz SG, Braun AR, Carr WS, Picchioni D, Balkin TJ, Fukunaga M, Duyn JH. Decoupling of the brain&#8217;s default mode network during deep sleep. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2009;106:11376&#8211;11381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2708777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19549821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horovitz SG, Fukunaga M, de Zwart JA, van Gelderen P, Fulton SC, Balkin TJ, Duyn JH. Low frequency BOLD fluctuations during resting wakefulness and light sleep: a simultaneous EEG-fMRI study. Hum Brain Mapp. 2008;29:671&#8211;682.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6871022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17598166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huppi PS, Dubois J. Diffusion tensor imaging of brain development. Semin Fetal Neonatal Med. 2006;11:489&#8211;497.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16962837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huppi PS, Warfield S, Kikinis R, Barnes PD, Zientara GP, Jolesz FA, Tsuji MK, Volpe JJ. Quantitative magnetic resonance imaging of brain development in premature and mature newborns. Ann Neurol. 1998;43:224&#8211;235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9485064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huttenlocher PR. Synaptic density in human frontal cortex&#8212;developmental changes and effects of aging. Brain Res. 1979;163:195&#8211;205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">427544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inder TE, Warfield SK, Wang H, Huppi PS, Volpe JJ. Abnormal cerebral structure is present at term in premature infants. Pediatrics. 2005;115:286&#8211;294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15687434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Innocenti GM, Price DJ. Exuberance in the development of cortical networks. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2005;6:955&#8211;965.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16288299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenkins GM, Watts DG. Spectral analysis and its applications. San Francisco (CA): Holden-Day; 1968.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang CK, Burgund ED, Lugar HM, Petersen SE, Schlaggar BL. Comparison of functional activation foci in children and adults using a common stereotactic space. Neuroimage. 2003;19:16&#8211;28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12781724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelly AM, Di Martino A, Uddin LQ, Shehzad Z, Gee DG, Reiss PT, Margulies DS, Castellanos FX, Milham MP. Development of anterior cingulate functional connectivity from late childhood to early adulthood. Cereb Cortex. 2009;19:640&#8211;657.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18653667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kostovic I, Jovanov-Milosevic N. The development of cerebral connections during the first 20-45 weeks&#8217; gestation. Semin Fetal Neonatal Med. 2006;11:415&#8211;422.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16962836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kostovic I, Rakic P. Developmental history of the transient subplate zone in the visual and somatosensory cortex of the macaque monkey and human brain. J Comp Neurol. 1990;297:441&#8211;470.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2398142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lagercrantz H, Changeux JP. The emergence of human consciousness: from fetal to neonatal life. Pediatr Res. 2009;65:255&#8211;260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19092726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lancaster JL, Glass TG, Lankipalli BR, Downs H, Mayberg H, Fox PT. A modality-independent approach to spatial normalization of tomographic images of the human brain. Hum Brain Mapp. 1995;3:209&#8211;223.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson-Prior LJ, Zempel JM, Nolan TS, Prior FW, Snyder AZ, Raichle ME. Cortical network functional connectivity in the descent to sleep. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2009;106:4489&#8211;4494.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2657465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19255447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin W, Zhu Q, Gao W, Chen Y, Toh CH, Styner M, Gerig G, Smith JK, Biswal B, Gilmore JH. Functional connectivity MR imaging reveals cortical functional connectivity in the developing brain. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 2008;29:1883&#8211;1889.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2583167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18784212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu WC, Flax JF, Guise KG, Sukul V, Benasich AA. Functional connectivity of the sensorimotor area in naturally sleeping infants. Brain Res. 2008;1223:42&#8211;49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18599026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Logothetis NK. The neural basis of the blood-oxygen-level-dependent functional magnetic resonance imaging signal. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 2002;357:1003&#8211;1037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1693017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12217171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long XY, Zuo XN, Kiviniemi V, Yang Y, Zou QH, Zhu CZ, Jiang TZ, Yang H, Gong QY, Wang L, et al. Default mode network as revealed with multiple methods for resting-state functional MRI analysis. J Neurosci Methods. 2008;171:349&#8211;355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18486233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lowe MJ, Mock BJ, Sorenson JA. Functional connectivity in single and multislice echoplanar imaging using resting-state fluctuations. Neuroimage. 1998;7:119&#8211;132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9558644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathur AM, Neil JJ, McKinstry RC, Inder TE. Transport, monitoring, and successful brain MR imaging in unsedated neonates. Pediatr Radiol. 2008;38:260&#8211;264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18175110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neil J, Miller J, Mukherjee P, Huppi PS. Diffusion tensor imaging of normal and injured developing human brain&#8212;a technical review. NMR Biomed. 2002;15:543&#8211;552.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12489100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niedermeyer E, Lopes da Silva FH. Electroencephalography: basic principles, clinical applications, and related fields. Philadelphia: Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins; 2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nosarti C, Rushe TM, Woodruff PW, Stewart AL, Rifkin L, Murray RM. Corpus callosum size and very preterm birth: relationship to neuropsychological outcome. Brain. 2004;127:2080&#8211;2089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15289268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojemann JG, Akbudak E, Snyder AZ, McKinstry RC, Raichle ME, Conturo TE. Anatomic localization and quantitative analysis of gradient refocused echo-planar fMRI susceptibility artifacts. Neuroimage. 1997;6:156&#8211;167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9344820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Partridge SC, Mukherjee P, Henry RG, Miller SP, Berman JI, Jin H, Lu Y, Glenn OA, Ferriero DM, Barkovich AJ, et al. Diffusion tensor imaging: serial quantitation of white matter tract maturity in premature newborns. Neuroimage. 2004;22:1302&#8211;1314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15219602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penn AA, Shatz CJ. Brain waves and brain wiring: the role of endogenous and sensory-driven neural activity in development. Pediatr Res. 1999;45:447&#8211;458.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10203134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peterson BS, Vohr B, Staib LH, Cannistraci CJ, Dolberg A, Schneider KC, Katz KH, Westerveld M, Sparrow S, Anderson AW, et al. Regional brain volume abnormalities and long-term cognitive outcome in preterm infants. JAMA. 2000;284:1939&#8211;1947.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11035890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinsk MA, Kastner S. Neuroscience: unconscious networking. Nature. 2007;447:46&#8211;47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17476253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raichle ME, MacLeod AM, Snyder AZ, Powers WJ, Gusnard DA, Shulman GL. A default mode of brain function. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2001;98:676&#8211;682.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC14647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11209064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rowland DJ, Garbow JR, Laforest R, Snyder AZ. Registration of [18F]FDG microPET and small-animal MRI. Nucl Med Biol. 2005;32:567&#8211;572.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16026703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shatz CJ. Emergence of order in visual system development. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1996;93:602&#8211;608.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC40098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8570602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shmuel A, Leopold DA. Neuronal correlates of spontaneous fluctuations in fMRI signals in monkey visual cortex: implications for functional connectivity at rest. Hum Brain Mapp. 2008;29:751&#8211;761.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6870786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18465799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talairach J, Tournoux P. Co-planar stereotaxic atlas of the human brain: 3-D proportional system: an approach to cerebral imaging. New York: Thieme Medical; 1988.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomason ME, Chang CE, Glover GH, Gabrieli JD, Greicius MD, Gotlib IH. Default-mode function and task-induced deactivation have overlapping brain substrates in children. Neuroimage. 2008;41:1493&#8211;1503.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2735193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18482851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vanhatalo S, Kaila K. Development of neonatal EEG activity: from phenomenology to physiology. Semin Fetal Neonatal Med. 2006;11:471&#8211;478.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17018268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vincent JL, Patel GH, Fox MD, Snyder AZ, Baker JT, Van Essen DC, Zempel JM, Snyder LH, Corbetta M, Raichle ME. Intrinsic functional architecture in the anaesthetized monkey brain. Nature. 2007;447:83&#8211;86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17476267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodward LJ, Anderson PJ, Austin NC, Howard K, Inder TE. Neonatal MRI to predict neurodevelopmental outcomes in preterm infants. N Engl J Med. 2006;355:685&#8211;694.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16914704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu C, Liu Y, Li J, Zhou Y, Wang K, Tian L, Qin W, Jiang T, Li K. Altered functional connectivity of primary visual cortex in early blindness. Hum Brain Mapp. 2008;29:533&#8211;543.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6871175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17525980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle><PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Owner="NLM" Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE"><PMID Version="1">34876816</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1176-6336</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>17</Volume><PubDate><Year>2021</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Therapeutics and clinical risk management</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ther Clin Risk Manag</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Chronic Intractable Pruritus in Chronic Kidney Disease Patients: Prevalence, Impact, and Management Challenges - A Narrative Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1267</StartPage><EndPage>1282</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1267-1282</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2147/TCRM.S310550</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Chronic kidney disease (CKD) is recognized as a leading public health problem and causes numerous health complications. One of the most common and burdensome dermatological symptoms affecting patients undergoing dialysis is CKD-associated pruritus (CKD-aP). This condition not only has a negative impact on sleep, mood, daily activities, and quality of life but also increases the mortality risk of hemodialyzed patients. Despite that, this condition is greatly underestimated in clinical practice. Due to the complex and still not fully understood etiopathogenesis of CKD-aP, the choice of an effective therapy remains a challenge for clinicians. Most common therapeutic algorithms use topical treatment, phototherapy, and various systemic approaches. This review aimed to summarize most recent theories about the pathogenesis, clinical features, and treatment of CKD-aP.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#169; 2021 &#346;wierczy&#324;ska et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>&#346;wierczy&#324;ska</LastName><ForeName>Karolina</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0417-2745</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, Venereology and Allergology, Wroclaw Medical University, Wroclaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bia&#322;ynicki-Birula</LastName><ForeName>Rafa&#322;</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2603-4220</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, Venereology and Allergology, Wroclaw Medical University, Wroclaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Szepietowski</LastName><ForeName>Jacek C</ForeName><Initials>JC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0766-6342</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, Venereology and Allergology, Wroclaw Medical University, Wroclaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>New Zealand</Country><MedlineTA>Ther Clin Risk Manag</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101253281</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1176-6336</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chronic kidney disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chronic kidney disease&#8211;associated pruritus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">treatment</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Jacek Szepietowski reports personal fees from AbbVie, Leo Pharma, Menlo Therapeutics, Novartis, Pierre-Fabre, Sandoz Sanofi-Genzyme, Trevi, and Viofor, personal fees from AbbVie, Bauch, Eli-Lilly, Leo-Pharma, Novartis, and Sanofi-Genzyme, and personal fees from AbbVie, Amgen, Behringer Ingelheim, Galapagos, Incyte, InflaRx, Janssen-Cilag, Leo Pharma, Menlo Therapeutics, Merck, Novartis, Pfizer, Regeneron, Trevi, and UCB, outside the submitted work. The authors declare no other conflicts of interest in this work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34876816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8643219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/TCRM.S310550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">310550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Song J, Xian D, Yang L, Xiong X, Lai R, Zhong J. Pruritus: progress toward pathogenesis and treatment. Biomed Res Int. 2018;2018:9625936. doi:10.1155/2018/9625936</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2018/9625936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5925168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29850592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Kidney Foundation. K/DOQI clinical practice guidelines for chronic kidney disease: evaluation, classification, and stratification. Am J Kidney Dis. 2002;39(2 Suppl 1):S1&#8211;S266.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11904577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill NR, Fatoba ST, Oke JL, et al. Global prevalence of chronic kidney disease - a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One. 2016;11(7):e0158765. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0158765</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0158765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4934905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27383068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv JC, Zhang LX. Prevalence and disease burden of chronic kidney disease. Adv Exp Med Biol. 2019;1165:3&#8211;15. doi:10.1007/978-981-13-8871-2_1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-981-13-8871-2_1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31399958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson-Bostom L, DiGiovanna JJ. Cutaneous manifestations of end-stage renal disease. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2000;43(6):975&#8211;990. doi:10.1067/mjd.2000.110651</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1067/mjd.2000.110651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11100013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel TS, Freedman BI, Yosipovitch G. An update on pruritus associated with CKD. Am J Kidney Dis. 2007;50(1):11&#8211;20. doi:10.1053/j.ajkd.2007.03.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/j.ajkd.2007.03.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17591521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suse&#322; J, Batycka-Baran A, Reich A, Szepietowski JC. Uraemic pruritus markedly affects the quality of life and depressive symptoms in haemodialysis patients with end-stage renal disease. Acta Derm Venereol. 2014;94(3):276&#8211;281. doi:10.2340/00015555-1749</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2340/00015555-1749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24217858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mollanazar NK, Koch SD, Yosipovitch G. Epidemiology of chronic pruritus: where have we been and where are we going? Curr Dermatol Rep. 2015;4(1):20&#8211;29. doi:10.1007/s13671-014-0093-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13671-014-0093-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szepietowski JC, Balaskas E, Taube KM, Taberly A, Dupuy P; Uraemic Xerosis Working Group. Quality of life in patients with uraemic xerosis and pruritus. Acta Derm Venereol. 2011;91(3):313&#8211;317. doi:10.2340/00015555-1075</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2340/00015555-1075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21369686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mettang T. Pruritus in renal disease. In: Carstens E, Akiyama T, editors. Itch: Mechanisms and Treatment. Boca Raton (FL): CRC Press/Taylor &amp; Francis; 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Urbonas A, Schwartz RA, Szepietowski JC. Uremic pruritus &#8211; an update. Am J Nephrol. 2001;21:343&#8211;350. doi:10.1159/000046272</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000046272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11684792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pisoni RL, Wikstr&#246;m B, Elder SJ, et al. Pruritus in haemodialysis patients: international results from the Dialysis Outcomes and Practice Patterns Study (DOPPS). Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2006;21(12):3495&#8211;3505. doi:10.1093/ndt/gfl461</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfl461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16968725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rayner HC, Larkina M, Wang M, et al. International comparisons of prevalence, awareness, and treatment of pruritus in people on hemodialysis. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2017;12(12):2000&#8211;2007. doi:10.2215/CJN.03280317</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2215/CJN.03280317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5718267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28923831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimata N, Fuller DS, Saito A, et al. Pruritus in hemodialysis patients: results from the Japanese Dialysis Outcomes and Practice Patterns Study (JDOPPS). Hemodial Int. 2014;18(3):657&#8211;667. doi:10.1111/hdi.12158</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/hdi.12158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24766224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weisshaar E, Weiss M, Passlick-Deetjen J, Tschulena U, Maleki K, Mettang T. Laboratory and dialysis characteristics in hemodialysis patients suffering from chronic itch&#8211;results from a representative cross-sectional study. BMC Nephrol. 2015;16:184. doi:10.1186/s12882-015-0177-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12882-015-0177-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4632673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26530958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu X, Sang Y, Yang M, Chen X, Tang W. Prevalence of chronic kidney disease-associated pruritus among adult dialysis patients: a meta-analysis of cross-sectional studies. Medicine (Baltimore). 2018;97(21):e10633. doi:10.1097/MD.0000000000010633</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000010633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6392722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29794739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Min JW, Kim SH, Kim YO, et al. Comparison of uremic pruritus between patients undergoing hemodialysis and peritoneal dialysis. Kidney Res Clin Pract. 2016;35(2):107&#8211;113. doi:10.1016/j.krcp.2016.02.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.krcp.2016.02.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4919557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27366666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu HY, Peng YS, Chen HY, et al. A comparison of uremic pruritus in patients receiving peritoneal dialysis and hemodialysis. Medicine (Baltimore). 2016;95(9):e2935. doi:10.1097/MD.0000000000002935</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000002935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4782884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26945400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakamoto H, Kobayashi T, Noguchi T, et al. Prevalence and severity of itching in patients with end-stage renal disease: treatment with nalfurafine hydrochloride. Blood Purif. 2019;47(suppl 2):45&#8211;49. doi:10.1159/000496637</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000496637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30943482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sukul N, Speyer E, Tu C, et al. Pruritus and patient reported outcomes in non-dialysis CKD. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2019;14(5):673&#8211;681. doi:10.2215/CJN.09600818</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2215/CJN.09600818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6500934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30975656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solak B, Acikgoz SB, Sipahi S, Erdem T. Epidemiology and determinants of pruritus in pre-dialysis chronic kidney disease patients. Int Urol Nephrol. 2016;48(4):585&#8211;591. doi:10.1007/s11255-015-1208-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11255-015-1208-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26762886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reszke R, Kili&#347;-Pstrusi&#324;ska K, Szepietowski JC. Chronic kidney disease-associated itch (CKD-aI) in children-a narrative review. Toxins (Basel). 2021;13(7):450. doi:10.3390/toxins13070450</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins13070450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8309841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34209560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mettang T, Pauli-Magnus C, Alscher DM. Uraemic pruritus&#8211;new perspectives and insights from recent trials. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2002;17(9):1558&#8211;1563. doi:10.1093/ndt/17.9.1558</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/17.9.1558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12198205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wojtowicz-Prus E, Kili&#347;-Pstrusi&#324;ska K, Reich A, et al. Chronic kidney disease-associated pruritus in children. Acta Derm Venereol. 2016;96(7):938&#8211;942. doi:10.2340/00015555-2454</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2340/00015555-2454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27171238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weisshaar E, Matterne U, Mettang T. How do nephrologists in haemodialysis units consider the symptom of itch? Results of a survey in Germany. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2009;24(4):1328&#8211;1330. doi:10.1093/ndt/gfn769</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfn769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19155533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szepietowski JC, Reich A, Schwartz RA. Uraemic xerosis. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2004;19(11):2709&#8211;2712. doi:10.1093/ndt/gfh480</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfh480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15328388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wojtowicz-Prus E, Kili&#347;-Pstrusi&#324;ska K, Reich A, et al. Disturbed skin barrier in children with chronic kidney disease. Pediatr Nephrol. 2015;30(2):333&#8211;338. doi:10.1007/s00467-014-2932-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00467-014-2932-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4282711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25127919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goicoechea M, de Sequera P, Ochando A, Andrea C, Caramelo C. Uremic pruritus: an unresolved problem in hemodialysis patients. Nephron. 1999;82(1):73&#8211;74. doi:10.1159/000045371</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000045371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10224488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young AW Jr, Sweeney EW, David DS, et al. Dermatologic evaluation of pruritus in patients on hemodialysis. N Y State J Med. 1973;73(22):2670&#8211;2674.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4519082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mettang T, Kremer AE. Uremic pruritus. Kidney Int. 2015;87(4):685&#8211;691. doi:10.1038/ki.2013.454</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ki.2013.454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24402092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morton CA, Lafferty M, Hau C, Henderson I, Jones M, Lowe JG. Pruritus and skin hydration during dialysis. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 1996;11(10):2031&#8211;2036. doi:10.1093/oxfordjournals.ndt.a027092</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.ndt.a027092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8918718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yosipovitch G, Duque MI, Patel TS, et al. Skin barrier structure and function and their relationship to pruritus in end-stage renal disease. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2007;22(11):3268&#8211;3272. doi:10.1093/ndt/gfm375</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfm375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17595180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhyani M, Ganji MR, Samadi N, Khamesan B, Daneshpazhooh M. Pruritus in hemodialysis patients. BMC Dermatol. 2005;5:7. doi:10.1186/1471-5945-5-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-5945-5-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1184066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15975150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okada K, Matsumoto K. Effect of skin care with an emollient containing a high water content on mild uremic pruritus. Ther Apher Dial. 2004;8(5):419&#8211;422. doi:10.1111/j.1526-0968.2004.00175.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1526-0968.2004.00175.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15663539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal P, Garg V, Karagaiah P, Szepietowski JC, Grabbe S, Goldust M. Chronic kidney disease-associated pruritus. Toxins. 2021;13(8):527. doi:10.3390/toxins13080527</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins13080527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8402524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34437400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimmel M, Alscher DM, Dunst R, et al. The role of micro-inflammation in the pathogenesis of uraemic pruritus in haemodialysis patients. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2006;21(3):749&#8211;755. doi:10.1093/ndt/gfi204</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfi204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16249205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fallahzadeh MK, Roozbeh J, Geramizadeh B, Namazi MR. Interleukin-2 serum levels are elevated in patients with uremic pruritus: a novel finding with practical implications. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2011;26(10):3338&#8211;3344. doi:10.1093/ndt/gfr053</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfr053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21372257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko MJ, Peng YS, Chen HY, et al. Interleukin-31 is associated with uremic pruritus in patients receiving hemodialysis. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2014;71(6):1151&#8211;1159.e1. doi:10.1016/j.jaad.2014.08.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2014.08.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25270263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oweis AO, Al-Qarqaz F, Bodoor K, et al. Elevated interleukin 31 serum levels in hemodialysis patients are associated with uremic pruritus. Cytokine. 2021;138:155369. doi:10.1016/j.cyto.2020.155369</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cyto.2020.155369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33221158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinugasa E, Igawa K, Shimada H, et al. Anti-pruritic effect of nemolizumab in hemodialysis patients with uremic pruritus: a Phase II, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical study. Clin Exp Nephrol. 2021;25(8):875&#8211;884. doi:10.1007/s10157-021-02047-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10157-021-02047-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8260520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33754202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The European Uremic Toxins (EUTox) Database. Available from:
https://database.uremic-toxins.org/home.php. Accessed May
27, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh TR, Choi HS, Kim CS, et al. Hyperuricemia has increased the risk of progression of chronic kidney disease: propensity score matching analysis from the KNOW-CKD study. Sci Rep. 2019;9(1):6681. doi:10.1038/s41598-019-43241-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-43241-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6491556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31040373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang CP, Lu YC, Tsai IT, et al. Increased levels of total p-Cresylsulfate are associated with pruritus in patients with chronic kidney disease. Dermatology. 2016;232(3):363&#8211;370. doi:10.1159/000445429</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000445429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27161100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noh SH, Park K, Kim EJ. The incidence of pruritus and biochemical marker associated with pruritus in hemodialysis patients. Ann Dermatol. 2018;30(4):473&#8211;475. doi:10.5021/ad.2018.30.4.473</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5021/ad.2018.30.4.473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6029977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30065591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Gelder MK, Middel IR, Vernooij RWM, et al. Protein-bound uremic toxins in hemodialysis patients relate to residual kidney function, are not influenced by convective transport, and do not relate to outcome. Toxins (Basel). 2020;12(4):234. doi:10.3390/toxins12040234</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxins12040234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7232478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32272776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim SJ, Zhang X, Cho SB, Kim CH, Park HC, Moon SJ. Uremic solutes of indoxyl sulfate and p-cresol enhance protease-activated receptor-2 expression in vitro and in vivo in keratinocytes. Hum Exp Toxicol. 2021;40(1):113&#8211;123. doi:10.1177/0960327120945758</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0960327120945758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32757783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moon SJ, Kim HJ, Cho SB, et al. Epidermal proteinase-activated receptor-2 expression is increased in end-stage renal disease patients with pruritus: a pilot Study. Electrolyte Blood Press. 2014;12(2):74&#8211;79. doi:10.5049/EBP.2014.12.2.74</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5049/EBP.2014.12.2.74</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4297706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25606046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinhoff M, Neisius U, Ikoma A, et al. Proteinase-activated receptor-2 mediates itch: a novel pathway for pruritus in human skin. J Neurosci. 2003;23(15):6176&#8211;6180. doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.23-15-06176.2003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.23-15-06176.2003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6740542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12867500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Q, Zhang H, Ding JR, et al. UPLC-QTOF MS-based serum metabolomic profiling analysis reveals the molecular perturbations underlying uremic pruritus. Biomed Res Int. 2018;2018:4351674. doi:10.1155/2018/4351674</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2018/4351674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5818897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29546058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolanos CG, Pham NM, Mair RD, Meyer TW, Sirich TL. Metabolomic analysis of uremic pruritus in patients on hemodialysis. PLoS One. 2021;16(2):e0246765. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0246765</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0246765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7880487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33577623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verduzco HA, Shirazian S. CKD-associated pruritus: new insights into diagnosis, pathogenesis, and management. Kidney Int Rep. 2020;5(9):1387&#8211;1402. doi:10.1016/j.ekir.2020.04.027</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ekir.2020.04.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7486142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32954065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swarna SS, Aziz K, Zubair T, Qadir N, Khan M. Pruritus associated with chronic kidney disease: a comprehensive literature review. Cureus. 2019;11(7):e5256. doi:10.7759/cureus.5256</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.5256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6760874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31572641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blachley JD, Blankenship DM, Menter A, Parker TF 3rd, Knochel JP. Uremic pruritus: skin divalent ion content and response to ultraviolet phototherapy. Am J Kidney Dis. 1985;5(5):237&#8211;241. doi:10.1016/s0272-6386(85)80115-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0272-6386(85)80115-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4003393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Momose A, Kudo S, Sato M, et al. Calcium ions are abnormally distributed in the skin of haemodialysis patients with uraemic pruritus. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2004;19(8):2061&#8211;2066. doi:10.1093/ndt/gfh287</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfh287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15187190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tajbakhsh R, Joshaghani HR, Bayzayi F, Haddad M, Qorbani M. Association between pruritus and serum concentrations of parathormone, calcium and phosphorus in hemodialysis patients. Saudi J Kidney Dis Transpl. 2013;24(4):702&#8211;706. doi:10.4103/1319-2442.113858</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/1319-2442.113858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23816717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massry SG, Popovtzer MM, Coburn JW, Makoff DL, Maxwell MH, Kleeman CR. Intractable pruritus as a manifestation of secondary hyperparathyroidism in uremia: disappearance of itching after subtotal parathyroidectomy. N Engl J Med. 1968;279(13):697&#8211;700. doi:10.1056/NEJM196809262791308</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJM196809262791308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5670911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hampers CL, Katz AI, Wilson RE, Merrill JP. Disappearance of &#8220;uremic&#8221; itching after subtotal parathyroidectomy. N Engl J Med. 1968;279(13):695&#8211;697. doi:10.1056/NEJM196809262791307</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJM196809262791307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5670910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makhlough A, Emadi N, Sedighi O, Khademloo M, Bicmohamadi AR. Relationship between serum intact parathyroid hormone and pruritus in hemodialysis patients. Iran J Kidney Dis. 2013;7(1):42&#8211;46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23314141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ostlere LS, Taylor C, Baillod R, Wright S. Relationship between pruritus, transepidermal water loss, and biochemical markers of renal itch in haemodialysis patients. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 1994;9(9):1302&#8211;1304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7816295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho YL, Liu HN, Huang TP, Tarng DC. Uremic pruritus: roles of parathyroid hormone and substance P. J Am Acad Dermatol. 1997;36(4):538&#8211;543. doi:10.1016/s0190-9622(97)70240-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0190-9622(97)70240-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9092738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>St&#229;hle-B&#228;ckdahl M, H&#228;germark O, Lins LE, T&#246;rring O, Hilliges M, Johansson O. Experimental and immunohistochemical studies on the possible role of parathyroid hormone in uraemic pruritus. J Intern Med. 1989;225(6):411&#8211;415. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2796.1989.tb00104.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2796.1989.tb00104.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2746157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duque MI, Thevarajah S, Chan YH, Tuttle AB, Freedman BI, Yosipovitch G. Uremic pruritus is associated with higher kt/V and serum calcium concentration. Clin Nephrol. 2006;66(3):184&#8211;191. doi:10.5414/cnp6618460</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5414/cnp6618460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16995341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu T, Wang B, Liao X, Wang S. Clinical features and risk factors of pruritus in patients with chronic renal failure. Exp Ther Med. 2019;18(2):964&#8211;971. doi:10.3892/etm.2019.7588</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3892/etm.2019.7588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6639943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31384331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stockenhuber F, Kurz RW, Sertl K, Grimm G, Balcke P. Increased plasma histamine levels in uraemic pruritus. Clin Sci (Lond). 1990;79(5):477&#8211;482. doi:10.1042/cs0790477</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1042/cs0790477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2174315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gill DS, Fonseca VA, Barradas MA, Balliod R, Moorhead JF, Dandona P. Plasma histamine in patients with chronic renal failure and nephrotic syndrome. J Clin Pathol. 1991;44(3):243&#8211;245. doi:10.1136/jcp.44.3.243</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jcp.44.3.243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC496948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2013627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Filippi C, Regazzini R, Piazza V, et al. Uraemic pruritus is not related to plasma histamine concentrations. Clin Exp Dermatol. 1995;20(4):294&#8211;296. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2230.1995.tb01328.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2230.1995.tb01328.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8548985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francos GC, Kauh YC, Gittlen SD, et al. Elevated plasma histamine in chronic uremia. Effects of ketotifen on pruritus. Int J Dermatol. 1991;30(12):884&#8211;889. doi:10.1111/j.1365-4362.1991.tb04360.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-4362.1991.tb04360.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1816135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szepietowski J, Thepen T, van Vloten WA, Szepietowski T, Bihari IC. Pruritus and mast cell proliferation in the skin of haemodialysis patients. Inflamm Res. 1995;44(Suppl 1):S84&#8211;S85. doi:10.1007/BF01674408</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF01674408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8521016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leong SO, Tan CC, Lye WC, Lee EJ, Chan HL. Dermal mast cell density and pruritus in end-stage renal failure. Ann Acad Med Singap. 1994;23(3):327&#8211;329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7944243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dimkovi&#263; N, Djukanovi&#263; L, Radmilovi&#263; A, Boji&#263; P, Juloski T. Uremic pruritus and skin mast cells. Nephron. 1992;61(1):5&#8211;9. doi:10.1159/000186826</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000186826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1528340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsumoto M, Ichimaru K, Horie A. Pruritus and mast cell proliferation of the skin in end stage renal failure. Clin Nephrol. 1985;23(6):285&#8211;288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4028525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mettang T, Fritz P, Weber J, Machleidt C, H&#252;bel E, Kuhlmann U. Uremic pruritus in patients on hemodialysis or continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD). The role of plasma histamine and skin mast cells. Clin Nephrol. 1990;34(3):136&#8211;141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1699691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dugas-Breit S, Sch&#246;pf P, Dugas M, Schiffl H, Ru&#235;ff F, Przybilla B. Baseline serum levels of mast cell tryptase are raised in hemodialysis patients and associated with severity of pruritus. J Dtsch Dermatol Ges. 2005;3(5):343&#8211;347. doi:10.1111/j.1610-0387.2005.05706.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1610-0387.2005.05706.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16372800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerr PG, Argiles A, Mion C. Whole blood serotonin levels are markedly elevated in patients on dialytic therapy. Am J Nephrol. 1992;12(1&#8211;2):14&#8211;18. doi:10.1159/000168411</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000168411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1415359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balaskas EV, Bamihas GI, Karamouzis M, Voyiatzis G, Tourkantonis A. Histamine and serotonin in uremic pruritus: effect of ondansetron in CAPD-pruritic patients. Nephron. 1998;78(4):395&#8211;402. doi:10.1159/000044967</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000044967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9578065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar K, Singh SI. Neuraxial opioid-induced pruritus: an update. J Anaesthesiol Clin Pharmacol. 2013;29(3):303&#8211;307. doi:10.4103/0970-9185.117045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0970-9185.117045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3788225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24106351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergasa NV, Alling DW, Talbot TL, et al. Effects of naloxone infusions in patients with the pruritus of cholestasis. A double-blind, randomized, controlled trial. Ann Intern Med. 1995;123(3):161&#8211;167. doi:10.7326/0003-4819-123-3-199508010-00001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-123-3-199508010-00001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7598296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaiswal D, Uzans D, Hayden J, Kiberd BA, Tennankore KK. Targeting the opioid pathway for uremic pruritus: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Can J Kidney Health Dis. 2016;3:2054358116675345. doi:10.1177/2054358116675345</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/2054358116675345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5332085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28270926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manenti L, Tansinda P, Vaglio A. Uraemic pruritus: clinical characteristics, pathophysiology and treatment. Drugs. 2009;69(3):251&#8211;263. doi:10.2165/00003495-200969030-00002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2165/00003495-200969030-00002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19275270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umeuchi H, Togashi Y, Honda T, et al. Involvement of central mu-opioid system in the scratching behavior in mice, and the suppression of it by the activation of kappa-opioid system. Eur J Pharmacol. 2003;477(1):29&#8211;35. doi:10.1016/j.ejphar.2003.08.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2003.08.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14512095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieczorek A, Krajewski P, Kozio&#322;-Ga&#322;czy&#324;ska M, Szepietowski JC. Opioid receptors expression in the skin of haemodialysis patients suffering from uraemic pruritus. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2020;34(10):2368&#8211;2372. doi:10.1111/jdv.16360</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdv.16360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32170896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zakrzewska-Pniewska B, Jedras M. Is pruritus in chronic uremic patients related to peripheral somatic and autonomic neuropathy? Study by R-R interval variation test (RRIV) and by sympathetic skin response (SSR). Neurophysiol Clin. 2001;31(3):181&#8211;193. doi:10.1016/s0987-7053(01)00257-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0987-7053(01)00257-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11488229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johansson O, Hilliges M, St&#229;hle-B&#228;ckdahl M. Intraepidermal neuron-specific enolase (NSE)-immunoreactive nerve fibres: evidence for sprouting in uremic patients on maintenance hemodialysis. Neurosci Lett. 1989;99(3):281&#8211;286. doi:10.1016/0304-3940(89)90460-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0304-3940(89)90460-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2657508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fantini F, Baraldi A, Sevignani C, Spattini A, Pincelli C, Giannetti A. Cutaneous innervation in chronic renal failure patients. An immunohistochemical study. Acta Derm Venereol. 1992;72(2):102&#8211;105. doi:10.2340/0001555572102105</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2340/0001555572102105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1350391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papoiu AD, Emerson NM, Patel TS, et al. Voxel-based morphometry and arterial spin labeling fMRI reveal neuropathic and neuroplastic features of brain processing of itch in end-stage renal disease. J Neurophysiol. 2014;112(7):1729&#8211;1738. doi:10.1152/jn.00827.2013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/jn.00827.2013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4157178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24944217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sorour NE, Elesawy FM, Tabl HA, Ibrahim ME, Akl EM. Evaluation of serum levels of neurotrophin 4 and brain-derived nerve growth factor in uremic pruritus patients. Clin Cosmet Investig Dermatol. 2019;12:109&#8211;114. doi:10.2147/CCID.S190917</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/CCID.S190917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6371925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30799944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra SK, Hoon MA. The cells and circuitry for itch responses in mice. Science. 2013;340(6135):968&#8211;971. doi:10.1126/science.1233765</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1233765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3670709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23704570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimizu Y, Sonoda A, Nogi C, et al. B-type (brain) natriuretic peptide and pruritus in hemodialysis patients. Int J Nephrol Renovasc Dis. 2014;7:329&#8211;335. doi:10.2147/IJNRD.S65929</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJNRD.S65929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4149441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25187733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Kroes S, Smeenk G. Serum vitamin A levels and pruritus in patients on hemodialysis. Dermatologica. 1983;166(4):199&#8211;202. doi:10.1159/000249867</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000249867</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6852332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathur VS, Lindberg J, Germain M, et al. A longitudinal study of uremic pruritus in hemodialysis patients. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2010;5(8):1410&#8211;1419. doi:10.2215/CJN.00100110</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2215/CJN.00100110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2924419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20558560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Combs SA, Teixeira JP, Germain MJ. Pruritus in kidney disease. Semin Nephrol. 2015;35(4):383&#8211;391. doi:10.1016/j.semnephrol.2015.06.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.semnephrol.2015.06.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5497472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26355256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss M, Mettang T, Tschulena U, Passlick-Deetjen J, Weisshaar E. Prevalence of chronic itch and associated factors in haemodialysis patients: a representative cross-sectional study. Acta Derm Venereol. 2015;95(7):816&#8211;821. doi:10.2340/00015555-2087</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2340/00015555-2087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25740325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heisig M, Reich A, Szepietowski JC. Is uremic pruritus still an important clinical problem in maintenance hemodialysis patients? J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2016;30(12):e198&#8211;e199. doi:10.1111/jdv.13524</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdv.13524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26616469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozen N, Cinar FI, Askin D, Mut D. Uremic pruritus and associated factors in hemodialysis patients: a multi-center study. Kidney Res Clin Pract. 2018;37(2):138&#8211;147. doi:10.23876/j.krcp.2018.37.2.138</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.23876/j.krcp.2018.37.2.138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6027816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29971209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minato S, Hirai K, Morino J, et al. Factors associated with uremic pruritus in patients undergoing peritoneal dialysis. Int J Nephrol Renovasc Dis. 2020;13:1&#8211;9. doi:10.2147/IJNRD.S224871</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJNRD.S224871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6969704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32021382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szepietowski JC, Sikora M, Kusztal M, Salomon J, Magott M, Szepietowski T. Uremic pruritus: a clinical study of maintenance hemodialysis patients. J Dermatol. 2002;29(10):621&#8211;627. doi:10.1111/j.1346-8138.2002.tb00191.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1346-8138.2002.tb00191.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12432992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zucker I, Yosipovitch G, David M, Gafter U, Boner G. Prevalence and characterization of uremic pruritus in patients undergoing hemodialysis: uremic pruritus is still a major problem for patients with end-stage renal disease. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2003;49(5):842&#8211;846. doi:10.1016/s0190-9622(03)02478-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0190-9622(03)02478-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14576662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rad M, Jaghouri E, Sharifipour F, Rakhshani M. The effects of cool dialysate on pruritus status during hemodialysis of patients with chronic renal failure: a controlled randomized clinical trial. Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2017;19(1). Available from: https://www.sid.ir/en/journal/ViewPaper.aspx?id=520984</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>St&#228;nder S, Augustin M, Reich A, et al. Pruritus assessment in clinical trials: consensus recommendations from the International Forum for the Study of Itch (IFSI) Special Interest Group Scoring Itch in Clinical Trials. Acta Derm Venereol. 2013;93(5):509&#8211;514. doi:10.2340/00015555-1620</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2340/00015555-1620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23624777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phan NQ, Blome C, Fritz F, et al. Assessment of pruritus intensity: prospective study on validity and reliability of the visual analogue scale, numerical rating scale and verbal rating scale in 471 patients with chronic pruritus. Acta Derm Venereol. 2012;92(5):502&#8211;507. doi:10.2340/00015555-1246</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2340/00015555-1246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22170091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nochaiwong S, Ruengorn C, Awiphan R, et al. Development of a multidimensional assessment tool for uraemic pruritus: Uraemic Pruritus in Dialysis Patients (UP-Dial). Br J Dermatol. 2017;176(6):1516&#8211;1524. doi:10.1111/bjd.15268</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bjd.15268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28012182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Chen FL, Zhao XR, et al. The reliability and validity of the 14-item uremic pruritus in dialysis patients scale (Chinese version scale). Chin J Blood Purif. 2019;18:575&#8211;578.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>&#346;wierczy&#324;ska K, Krajewski P, Reszke R, et al. Uraemic Pruritus in Dialysis Patient (UP-Dial) questionnaire: creation and validation of the Polish language version. Adv Dermatol Allergol. 2021. doi:10.5114/ada.2021.107271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5114/ada.2021.107271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tessari G, Dalle Vedove C, Loschiavo C, et al. The impact of pruritus on the quality of life of patients undergoing dialysis: a single centre cohort study. J Nephrol. 2009;22(2):241&#8211;248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19384842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim MK, Elshahid AR, El Baz TZ, Elazab RM, Elhoseiny SA, Elsaie ML. Impact of uraemic pruritus on quality of life among end stage renal disease patients on dialysis. J Clin Diagn Res. 2016;10(3):WC01&#8211;WC5. doi:10.7860/JCDR/2016/16273.7488</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7860/JCDR/2016/16273.7488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4843366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27134981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moncrieff G, Cork M, Lawton S, Kokiet S, Daly C, Clark C. Use of emollients in dry-skin conditions: consensus statement. Clin Exp Dermatol. 2013;38(3):231&#8211;238. doi:10.1111/ced.12104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ced.12104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23517354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balaskas E, Szepietowski JC, Bessis D, et al. Randomized, double-blind study with glycerol and paraffin in uremic xerosis. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2011;6(4):748&#8211;752. doi:10.2215/CJN.05490610</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2215/CJN.05490610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3069365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21258039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen YC, Chiu WT, Wu MS. Therapeutic effect of topical gamma-linolenic acid on refractory uremic pruritus. Am J Kidney Dis. 2006;48(1):69&#8211;76. doi:10.1053/j.ajkd.2006.03.082</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/j.ajkd.2006.03.082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16797388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castello M, Milani M. Efficacy of topical hydrating and emollient lotion containing 10% urea ISDIN&#174; plus dexpanthenol (Ureadin Rx 10) in the treatment of skin xerosis and pruritus in hemodialyzed patients: an open prospective pilot trial. G Ital Dermatol Venereol. 2011;146(5):321&#8211;325.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21956268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breneman DL, Cardone JS, Blumsack RF, Lather RM, Searle EA, Pollack VE. Topical capsaicin for treatment of hemodialysis-related pruritus. J Am Acad Dermatol. 1992;26(1):91&#8211;94. doi:10.1016/0190-9622(92)70013-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0190-9622(92)70013-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1732343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarng DC, Cho YL, Liu HN, Huang TP. Hemodialysis-related pruritus: a double-blind, placebo-controlled, crossover study of capsaicin 0.025% cream. Nephron. 1996;72(4):617&#8211;622. doi:10.1159/000188949</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000188949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8730431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makhlough A, Ala S, Haj-Heydari Z, Kashi Z, Bari A. Topical capsaicin therapy for uremic pruritus in patients on hemodialysis. Iran J Kidney Dis. 2010;4(2):137&#8211;140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20404425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szepietowski JC, Reich A, Szepietowski T. Emollients with endocannabinoids in the treatment of uremic pruritus: discussion of the therapeutic options. Ther Apher Dial. 2005;9(3):277&#8211;279. doi:10.1111/j.1774-9987.2005.00271.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1774-9987.2005.00271.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15967006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuypers DR, Claes K, Evenepoel P, Maes B, Vanrenterghem Y. A prospective proof of concept study of the efficacy of tacrolimus ointment on uraemic pruritus (UP) in patients on chronic dialysis therapy. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2004;19(7):1895&#8211;1901. doi:10.1093/ndt/gfh202</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfh202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15150348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pauli-Magnus C, Klumpp S, Alscher DM, Kuhlmann U, Mettang T. Short-term efficacy of tacrolimus ointment in severe uremic pruritus. Perit Dial Int. 2000;20(6):802&#8211;803. doi:10.1177/089686080002000641</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/089686080002000641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11216583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duque MI, Yosipovitch G, Fleischer AB Jr, Willard J, Freedman BI. Lack of efficacy of tacrolimus ointment 0.1% for treatment of hemodialysis-related pruritus: a randomized, double-blind, vehicle-controlled study. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2005;52(3 Pt 1):519&#8211;521. doi:10.1016/j.jaad.2004.08.050</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2004.08.050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15761435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghorbani AR, Feily A, Khalili A, Dormanesh B. Lack of efficacy of topical calcineurin inhibitor pimecrolimus 1% on pruritus of severely uremic patients: a randomized double-blind study in 60 patients. Dermatitis. 2011;22(3):167&#8211;168. doi:10.2310/6620.2011.10110</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2310/6620.2011.10110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21569748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ada S, Se&#231;kin D, Budako&#287;lu I, Ozdemir FN. Treatment of uremic pruritus with narrowband ultraviolet B phototherapy: an open pilot study. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2005;53(1):149&#8211;151. doi:10.1016/j.jaad.2004.12.052</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2004.12.052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15965439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang TJ, Lan LC, Lu CS, et al. Efficacy of narrowband ultraviolet phototherapy on renal pruritus. J Clin Nurs. 2014;23(11&#8211;12):1593&#8211;1602. doi:10.1111/jocn.12252</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jocn.12252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24131447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sherjeena PB, Binitha MP, Rajan U, et al. A controlled trial of narrowband ultraviolet B phototherapy for the treatment of uremic pruritus. Indian J Dermatol Venereol Leprol. 2017;83(2):247&#8211;249. doi:10.4103/0378-6323.198464</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0378-6323.198464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28164894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sapam R, Waikhom R. Role of narrow band ultra violet radiation as an add-on therapy in peritoneal dialysis patients with refractory uremic pruritus. World J Nephrol. 2018;7(4):84&#8211;89. doi:10.5527/wjn.v7.i4.84</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5527/wjn.v7.i4.84</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6081389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30090706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko MJ, Yang JY, Wu HY, et al. Narrowband ultraviolet B phototherapy for patients with refractory uraemic pruritus: a randomized controlled trial. Br J Dermatol. 2011;165(3):633&#8211;639. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2133.2011.10448.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2133.2011.10448.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21668425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakur A, Chaudhari S, Chaudhari P, Thakur M. Phototherapy as a treatment for Uremic Pruritus&#8212;A review. Gen Med. 2015;3:202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz IF, Iaina A. Uraemic pruritus. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 1999;14(4):834&#8211;839. doi:10.1093/ndt/14.4.834</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/14.4.834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10328453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lugon JR. Uremic pruritus: a review. Hemodial Int. 2005;9(2):180&#8211;188. doi:10.1111/j.1492-7535.2005.01130.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1492-7535.2005.01130.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16191067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weisshaar E, Dunker N, R&#246;hl FW, Gollnick H. Antipruritic effects of two different 5-HT3 receptor antagonists and an antihistamine in haemodialysis patients. Exp Dermatol. 2004;13(5):298&#8211;304. doi:10.1111/j.0906-6705.2004.00184.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.0906-6705.2004.00184.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15140020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilchrest BA, Stern RS, Steinman TI, Brown RS, Arndt KA, Anderson WW. Clinical features of pruritus among patients undergoing maintenance hemodialysis. Arch Dermatol. 1982;118(3):154&#8211;156. doi:10.1001/archderm.1982.01650150016012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/archderm.1982.01650150016012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7065661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berger TG, Steinhoff M. Pruritus and renal failure. Semin Cutan Med Surg. 2011;30(2):99&#8211;100. doi:10.1016/j.sder.2011.04.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sder.2011.04.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3692272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21767770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo GE, Spaziani M, Guidotti C, et al. Pruritus in chronic uremic patients in periodic hemodialysis. Treatment with terfenadine (an antagonist of histamine H1 receptors) (article in Italian). Minerva Urol Nefrol. 1986;38(4):443&#8211;447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2884733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirazian S, Aina O, Park Y, et al. Chronic kidney disease-associated pruritus: impact on quality of life and current management challenges. Int J Nephrol Renovasc Dis. 2017;10:11&#8211;26. doi:10.2147/IJNRD.S108045</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJNRD.S108045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5271405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28176969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amirkhanlou S, Rashedi A, Taherian J, Hafezi AA, Parsaei S. Comparison of gabapentin and ketotifen in treatment of uremic pruritus in hemodialysis patients. Pak J Med Sci. 2016;32(1):22&#8211;26. doi:10.12669/pjms.321.8547</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12669/pjms.321.8547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4795872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27022338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feily A, Dormanesh B, Ghorbani AR, et al. Efficacy of topical cromolyn sodium 4% on pruritus in uremic nephrogenic patients: a randomized double-blind study in 60 patients. Int J Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2012;50(7):510&#8211;513. doi:10.5414/cp201629</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5414/cp201629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22732382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eusebio-Alpapara KMV, Castillo RL, Dofitas BL. Gabapentin for uremic pruritus: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Int J Dermatol. 2020;59(4):412&#8211;422. doi:10.1111/ijd.14708</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijd.14708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31777066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simonsen E, Komenda P, Lerner B, et al. Treatment of uremic pruritus: a systematic review. Am J Kidney Dis. 2017;70(5):638&#8211;655. doi:10.1053/j.ajkd.2017.05.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/j.ajkd.2017.05.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28720208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rayner H, Baharani J, Smith S, Suresh V, Dasgupta I. Uraemic pruritus: relief of itching by gabapentin and pregabalin. Nephron Clin Pract. 2012;122(3&#8211;4):75&#8211;79. doi:10.1159/000349943</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000349943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23548570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ravindran A, Kunnath RP, Sunny A, Vimal B. Comparison of safety and efficacy of pregabalin versus gabapentin for the treatment of uremic pruritus in patients with chronic kidney disease on maintenance haemodialysis. Indian J Palliat Care. 2020;26(3):281&#8211;286. doi:10.4103/IJPC.IJPC_212_19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/IJPC.IJPC_212_19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7725189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33311867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solak Y, Biyik Z, Atalay H, et al. Pregabalin versus gabapentin in the treatment of neuropathic pruritus in maintenance haemodialysis patients: a prospective, crossover study. Nephrology (Carlton). 2012;17(8):710&#8211;717. doi:10.1111/j.1440-1797.2012.01655.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1797.2012.01655.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22909343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weisshaar E, Ofenloch RF. One step closer to alleviating uraemic pruritus. Nat Rev Nephrol. 2020;16(4):189&#8211;190. doi:10.1038/s41581-020-0251-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41581-020-0251-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31988499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fishbane S, Mathur V, Germain MJ, et al. Randomized controlled trial of difelikefalin for chronic pruritus in hemodialysis patients. Kidney Int Rep. 2020;5(5):600&#8211;610. doi:10.1016/j.ekir.2020.01.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ekir.2020.01.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7210745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32405581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fishbane S, Jamal A, Munera C, Wen W, Menzaghi F; KALM-1 Trial Investigators. A Phase 3 trial of difelikefalin in hemodialysis patients with pruritus. N Engl J Med. 2020;382(3):222&#8211;232. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa1912770</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1912770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31702883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wikstr&#246;m B, Gellert R, Ladefoged SD, et al. Kappa-opioid system in uremic pruritus: multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical studies. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2005;16(12):3742&#8211;3747. doi:10.1681/ASN.2005020152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1681/ASN.2005020152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16251241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumagai H, Ebata T, Takamori K, Muramatsu T, Nakamoto H, Suzuki H. Effect of a novel kappa-receptor agonist, nalfurafine hydrochloride, on severe itch in 337 haemodialysis patients: a Phase III, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2010;25(4):1251&#8211;1257. doi:10.1093/ndt/gfp588</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfp588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19926718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peer G, Kivity S, Agami O, et al. Randomised crossover trial of naltrexone in uraemic pruritus. Lancet. 1996;348(9041):1552&#8211;1554. doi:10.1016/s0140-6736(96)04176-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(96)04176-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8950882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pauli-Magnus C, Mikus G, Alscher DM, et al. Naltrexone does not relieve uremic pruritus: results of a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover study. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2000;11(3):514&#8211;519. doi:10.1681/ASN.V113514</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1681/ASN.V113514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10703675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathur VS, Kumar J, Crawford PW, Hait H, Sciascia T; TR02 Study Investigators. A multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of nalbuphine ER tablets for uremic pruritus. Am J Nephrol. 2017;46(6):450&#8211;458. doi:10.1159/000484573</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000484573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29253847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiroshige K, Kabashima N, Takasugi M, Kuroiwa A. Optimal dialysis improves uremic pruritus. Am J Kidney Dis. 1995;25(3):413&#8211;419. doi:10.1016/0272-6386(95)90102-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0272-6386(95)90102-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7872318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu HY, Huang JW, Tsai WC, et al. Prognostic importance and determinants of uremic pruritus in patients receiving peritoneal dialysis: a prospective cohort study. PLoS One. 2018;13(9):e0203474. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0203474</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0203474</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6124771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30183756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko MJ, Wu HY, Chen HY, et al. Uremic pruritus, dialysis adequacy, and metabolic profiles in hemodialysis patients: a prospective 5-year cohort study. PLoS One. 2013;8(8):e71404. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0071404</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0071404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3735516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23940749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cupisti A, Piccoli GB, Gallieni M. Charcoal for the management of pruritus and uremic toxins in patients with chronic kidney disease. Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens. 2020;29(1):71&#8211;79. doi:10.1097/MNH.0000000000000567</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MNH.0000000000000567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31725009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pederson JA, Matter BJ, Czerwinski AW, Llach F. Relief of idiopathic generalized pruritus in dialysis patients treated with activated oral charcoal. Ann Intern Med. 1980;93(3):446&#8211;448. doi:10.7326/0003-4819-93-3-446</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-93-3-446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7436164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto S, Kazama JJ, Omori K, et al. Continuous reduction of protein-bound uraemic toxins with improved oxidative stress by using the oral charcoal adsorbent AST-120 in haemodialysis patients. Sci Rep. 2015;5:14381. doi:10.1038/srep14381</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep14381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4585768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26395517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu PH, Tai YC, Yu MC, Lin IH, Kuo KL. Western and complementary alternative medicine treatment of uremic pruritus: a literature review. Tzu Chi Med J. 2021;33:350. doi:10.4103/tcmj.tcmj_151_20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/tcmj.tcmj_151_20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8532575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34760630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chou FF, Ho JC, Huang SC, Sheen-Chen SM. A study on pruritus after parathyroidectomy for secondary hyperparathyroidism. J Am Coll Surg. 2000;190(1):65&#8211;70. doi:10.1016/s1072-7515(99)00212-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s1072-7515(99)00212-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10625234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panuccio V, Tripepi R, Bellantoni M, et al. Pruritus and quality of life in renal transplant patients. Clin Transplant. 2017;31(3):e12893. doi:10.1111/ctr.12893</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ctr.12893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27988982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schricker S, Weisshaar E, Kupfer J, Mettang T. Prevalence of pruritus in a single cohort of long-term kidney transplant recipients. Acta Derm Venereol. 2020;100(4):adv00066. doi:10.2340/00015555-3421</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2340/00015555-3421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32052851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krajewski PK, Olczyk P, Krajewska M, Krajewski W, Szepietowski JC. Clinical characteristics of Itch in renal transplant recipients. Front Med (Lausanne). 2021;7:615334. doi:10.3389/fmed.2020.615334</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmed.2020.615334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7854568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33553209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panahi Y, Dashti-Khavidaki S, Farnood F, Noshad H, Lotfi M, Gharekhani A. Therapeutic effects of omega-3 fatty acids on chronic kidney disease-associated pruritus: a literature review. Adv Pharm Bull. 2016;6(4):509&#8211;514. doi:10.15171/apb.2016.064</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15171/apb.2016.064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5241408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28101457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim KH, Lee MS, Choi SM. Acupuncture for treating uremic pruritus in patients with end-stage renal disease: a systematic review. J Pain Symptom Manage. 2010;40(1):117&#8211;125. doi:10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2009.11.325</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2009.11.325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21796811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong W, He FF, You RY, et al. Acupuncture application in chronic kidney disease and its potential mechanisms. Am J Chin Med. 2018;46(6):1169&#8211;1185. doi:10.1142/S0192415X18500611</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1142/S0192415X18500611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30286626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim KH, Lee MS, Kim TH, Kang JW, Choi TY, Lee JD. Acupuncture and related interventions for symptoms of chronic kidney disease. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016;6:CD009440. doi:10.1002/14651858.CD009440.pub2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD009440.pub2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8406453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27349639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badiee Aval S, Ravanshad Y, Azarfar A, Mehrad-Majd H, Torabi S, Ravanshad S. A systematic review and meta-analysis of using acupuncture and acupressure for uremic pruritus. Iran J Kidney Dis. 2018;12(2):78&#8211;83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29507269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin CE, Clotet-Freixas S, Farragher JF, Hundemer GL. Have we just scratched the surface? A narrative review of uremic pruritus in 2020. Can J Kidney Health Dis. 2020;7:2054358120954024. doi:10.1177/2054358120954024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/2054358120954024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7573751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33117546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>